本字幕由志愿者义务贡献，采用许可协议
知识共享 署名-非商业性使用-相同方式共享 3.0 美国
Stanford University.
斯坦福大学
Okay, well, welcome to CS193P, Stanford CS193P.
欢迎参加 2017 年冬季学期斯坦福
This is Developing Applications for iOS, winter
CS193P 课程，iOS 应用程序开发
of 2017. Today we're going to talk a little bit about what
我们今天先会讲讲本课的主要内容
this class is about, and the prerequisites you need.
和上这门课之前你所需要具备的能力
Then I'm, really fast, gonna go over iOS and what's in it.
之后我会很快地过一遍什么是 iOS，由什么构成
And then, I'm gonna dive into a big, long demo.
最后我会带大家做一个很完整的示例程序
And this demo is gonna really quickly let you see what it's
给你们展示一下开发 iOS 程序是什么感觉
like to develop an application for iOS, so you can decide,
你们可以再决定
is this for me, or not? So, what are you gonna learn?
究竟适不适合你。这门课主要我们主要会讲
Well you're gonna learn to build cool apps, all right,
如何开发很酷的 app
that's, that's what we're here for. Why are these apps in iOS
当然了，你们来这里就是为了这个。可是为什么 iOS 上的程序这么 cool 呢？
cool? Well for a number of reasons, okay?
这其中有几个原因
One is they're in your back pocket,
首先是你可以随时
you can pull them out and show your friends on your phone,
把手机拿出来展示给他们看
a lot of them are networked so there're kind of social
许多 app 可以联网，而这些社交类的程序
apps and a lot of that can be a lot of fun.
通常都能给我们带来欢乐
Also if you decide to turn your app into a product it's
如果你决定发布你写的程序
really easy to get it out to customers via the App Store.
你能很轻松地通过 App Store 展示给顾客
You don't have to wrap it in a box and
你不再需要把程序
put it on a shelf somewhere anymore. You can get it out
用盒子包装好后放到货架上了
there real quick. And also you're going to see,
不仅上架的过程快，你马上会见识到
today even, it's really easy to build pretty complex
就算是很复杂的 app
app pretty quickly. So you get a lot of instant gratification
我们也能很轻松地写出来，让你马上就觉得
from building iOS apps. For those of you in
开发 iOS 程序很有成就感
computer science there's also this huge benefit, you're
对于那些选修计算机科学的同学们
gonna get to see a real life object-oriented programming
你们能实际观察到面向对象系统的应用
system. And not just object-oriented programming,
当然我们不只会讲面向对象编程
but we're going to use databases in this class, and
我们还会使用数据库
graphics, and multimedia, multi-threading, animation,
图形用户界面，多媒体，多线程，动画
networking, all these things. And
网络，等等
you're going to see it in a real world environment.
而且我们会在真实的情景下学习
So you take a lot of classes on these subjects
你们多半已经上了不少关于编程或是计算机的课了
and sometimes you get maybe a little disconnected from
相信有时候你会觉得那些课程
what's this like in the real world, well,
都有些脱离实际
you're gonna get to see it all in action here. Prerequisites,
我们这门课就是让你见识下这些抽象概念的实际运用
just boiling it down really easily. The prerequisite for
上这门课之前你所需要具备的能力
the class is object-oriented programming.
肯定少不了面向对象
You have to know object-oriented programming,
你必须要了解面向对象编程
I'm not gonna teach that in the class, I completely and
我绝不会在课上讲关于面向对象的知识
utterly assume it. And not only do you have to know it,
你还不能只是听说过面向对象
you have to have some experience doing it.
你还应该实际运用过
So that's why here at Stanford CS106 A and
换言之，你需要上过斯坦福 CS106 A 或 B
B are a hard prerequisite. You have to have taken those two,
这是硬性条件，你必须要上过至少其中一门
those are object-oriented programming classes. And
你将会在那些课程中学到面向对象编程的相关知识
then I just want to make sure you have some programming
其次是你要有些编程的经验
experience, so either you've done something outside
可以是你课外活动
of school, or you've taken CS107 or CS108 or CS110.
也可以是上过 CS107、CS108、CS110 其中的一个
CS108 is a particularly great prerequisite,
如果你不满足这些条件，CS108 是个不错的选择
that's object-oriented programming.
那门课会讲面向对象编程
So if you have a chance to take CS108 and
所以如果你需要但还没有去上一门这样的课
you haven't taken it yet, yeah, maybe taken it, and
你最好现在换成 CS108
then take this class the next time it's offered, all right?
等下次提供 CS193P 的时候再来上也不迟
So let's dive through what's in iOS really quickly here.
我们简单讲讲 iOS 系统的构成
I've divided it here into four layers.
我将 iOS 分为了 4 层
These layers are roughly close to the hardware.
越下面的越接近硬件
And then up close to the user. So that bottom layer close to
越上面的越接近用户。我们看到那个
the hardware, that's actually a UNIX operating system, okay?
最接近硬件的那层，那其实是 UNIX 操作系统
Just like macOS, iOS is a UNIX operating system at
就像 macOS 一样，iOS 也是基于 UNIX 操作系统
the bottom. None of these APIs are object oriented or
这些 API（应用程序接口）都不是面向对象的
anything, they're basically C, okay? For
因为它们基本上都是用 C 语言写出来的
the UNIX pretty much written in C, these API's are in C.
因为 UNIX 是用 C 语言写的，API 自然也是 C 风格的
We're gonna do no work at that level in this class, okay?
我们不会在这门课中涉及到这个层次的编程
This is an object-oriented programming only class,
我们只会涉及到有关于面向对象编程的内容
so we're not gonna be doing anything there.
不会和 C 打交道
So there's another layer right on top of that called core
在那一层之上是 Core Serviecs 层
services. Sometimes people refer to this as foundation,
这一层主要是 Foundation
but there's other things in this lever, layer,
但其实在这一层中除了 Foundation 以外
besides foundation. And this is an object oriented layer
还有其它的功能。这一层实际上是
on top of those things that were lower down. Okay, so
我们之前看到那一层经过了面向对象的封装
now you can do networking, file system, things like that,
实现网络传输，访问文件系统的 API
using object oriented API. But this is still non UI layer,
都是面向对象的。虽然这一层依旧不会涉及到用户界面
right? It's still kinda closer to the hardware. So I'll
这层离硬件还算近的，
definitely be teaching you a lot of stuff at this layer,
所以我们会在这上面多下点功夫
'cause you just need it to do the things you're gonna do.
因为这些是必不可少的
Now, there's another layer here, the media layer here I
下一层是媒体处理层
call it. This is a huge layer, which has 3D graphics, and
这一层包含 3D 绘制
audio playback and recording, image processing, video,
音频播放，录音，图像处理，视频等相关的功能。
all that stuff. Unfortunately I'm not gonna have a lot of
可惜我们并没有什么时间学习这些
time to spend here, even though it's a huge part of
即使这是 iOS 设备日常使用所需要的功能
what an iOS device does. iOS devices all pretty much have
所有的 iOS 设备都能被当作一个 iPods 使用
iPods in them, video iPods if you wanna think about it.
或者你也可以把它们叫做有显示屏的“iPods”
And so there's a lot here. Unfortunately I can't cover it
当然不止这些功能，不过我依然不能细讲这些
all. Because I'm gonna spend most of my time up here,
因为我们大部分时间都会花在这儿
which is the Cocoa Touch layer.
Cocoa Touch 层
This is where buttons and text fields and things are, but
这一层包含了按钮，文本字段等控件
also much more powerful objects like maps.
甚至还包括那些功能强大的类，比如地图
There's an object in Cocoa Touch which is a map object,
Cocoa Touch 层中定义了一个地图的类
it's pretty much the entire Maps application on
那基本包含了 iOS 上地图程序所有的功能
an iOS device, that you can drop right into a rectangle
你只需要把它放到你程序的界面上就行了
in your app. With almost no work.
除此之外你基本什么都不需要做
So, very powerful object to this layer. This is where
所以这一层的类都很好用
we're gonna spend the vast majority of our time,
我们大部分时间也会学习
building user interface apps at this layer.
如何在这个层面构建用户界面
That's a rough overview. Trying to explain all
大概 iOS 系统的构成就是这样
of iOS in two minutes is pretty much impossible, but
这么几分钟就完整地介绍 iOS 操作系统基本是不可能的
that's kind of what we're doing in this class. We're
但你应该大概知道这门课程大概会包括哪些内容了
gonna use all these components to get our work done.
iOS 开发是由以下几个部分构成的
Top level there, Xcode 8, is gonna be...
首先是 Xcode 8
everything we do is gonna be in Xcode 8.
我们所有事情都是在 Xcode 8 里完成的
The debugger, the editor, everything, building,
调试器，编辑器，编译，等等
it's all in Xcode 8. There's a little app, Instruments,
Xcode 8 都能搞定。我们还会用到 Instruments
that goes along with it, for performance and stuff, but
Xcode 附带的小程序，能用来检测程序的性能
pretty much it's all Xcode 8. Two, I'm gonna teach you
不过我们还是使用 Xcode 8 的时候比较多
a new programming language. So if you're computer science
然后我们将学一门新的编程语言
people, you know that learning different programming
学计算机科学的同学们应该知道
languages, really valuable skill.
多学会一门语言是很有用的
Not because you're necessarily gonna use all of them,
并不是说平常我们要把学过的语言都用上
some you might or might not use. But just the process of
这需要根据情况取舍
seeing how language designers pick and choose their syntax
不过光是研究设计语言这群人
and, and the feature set, is really valuable.
决定的语法和功能，你都应该得到些收获
So you'll get that I would think. It's a great language.
Swift 是世界上最好的语言
It was just invented in the last two or three years, so
它在两三年前（2014年）才被发明出来
it kind of incorporates the best of a lot of different
所以它集成了各种语言的精华
languages. So I'm gonna kind of blitzkrieg teach that to
我将会用前几周的时间用填鸭式教会你们
you in the first couple weeks. Frameworks: That's essentially
框架是必不可少的
things like the Cocoa Touch UIKit framework.
就比如 Cocoa Touch 的 UIKit 框架
It's where all the buttons and stuff are.
就是它包含了我们要用的按钮等控件
Foundation is that, kind of,
Foundation 框架，正如我们之前说的
mostly that Core Services layer.
主要是 Core Services 层的
But there's a lot of other ones like Core Data framework,
当然还有不少其它的框架，比如 Core Data 框架
object-oriented database,
面向对象的数据库
we'll be doing that in assignment five.
我们将会在第五个作业中用到
Also I talked about that map thing, that's in a framework
之前说的很牛的地图，那是 MapKit 框架里的
called MapKit. And there's also things in Core Motion,
你能通过 Core Motion 框架读取
like the accelerometer and the gyro in the device.
设备的加速度计和陀螺仪的数据
All those things, I'm gonna be teaching you many,
一路上我们将学到
many of these frameworks as we go on. And
越来越多的框架
last, but definitely not least, and very,
最后， 非常重要的
very important, is the design strategy for
是关于如何构建程序的设计模式
how to build apps, it's called MVC, model-view-controller.
MVC, 即 Model（模型）-View（视图）-Controller（控制器）
How many people already know MVC, have,
在场的同学有多少是听说过 MVC 的？
have learned in a different class?
有多少学过的？
See, so maybe half of you. I will spend the first part of
大概有一半吧。那我星期三
Wednesday's lecture telling you about MVC and what it is.
上课时再讲讲 MVC 的概念
We 100.0% have to use MVC when we develop apps for iOS.
我们在开发 iOS 程序的时候肯定会用到 MVC
There's really no other way to do it, if you do it any other
可以说这是你无可厚非的选择
way, you're swimming so up stream against the current of
如果你要另辟蹊径的话，那也只是逆水行舟
iOS, it's... You'll end up with a mess of an application,
你最终会发现你的程序乱成一团糟
okay, so we'll be going over that as well. This demo
所以我们会讲讲 MVC
that I'm gonna do, we're gonna build a calculator.
接下了我们要写一个计算器程序
A calculator's great because it's got a fairly simple UI,
因为它的界面很简单
but it's got a little bit of guts on the inside,
其实计算结果的部分
the actual calculating part. So
又有些难度
it's just complicated enough to start showing you MVC and
用它来示范 MVC 刚刚好
a lot of language features and things like that. But not so
能用到许多 Swift 语言的特性
complicated that I can't do an entire calculator, basically,
但又不会难到
in two lectures, okay, start to finish. All these topics up
我没法在两堂课内讲完。
here, you don't have to look at them now.
你不需要太在意现在你看到的这些
This is the slide to go look at after my lecture today and
在我讲完之后你自己再来看
say, hmm did I learn that, yeah,
问问自己我是否学会了
I think I got that. So
我是否掌握了
it's kind of a summary of what I'm gonna do. Since I'm not
这就是这个课程大纲的用法
gonna get back to the slides from the end of my demo,
既然我演示完之后多半下课了
it's just gonna be the end of the lecture.
不会再回到这一页
I'll tell you a little bit what's coming up.
我现在就先讲讲之后的课程安排
On Wednesday, I'll be continuing this demo, but
星期三我会继续编这个计算器
not until after I give you this talk about MVC,
但我肯定要先讲 MVC
because what we're gonna do in the calculator is apply MVC
因为下节课我们就要
to it, on Wednesday. And your first
在计算器中运用 MVC
programming assignment will go out on Wednesday, which is
星期三我们还会放出第一个编程作业
pretty much to replicate what I'm doing today and
你们只需要依葫芦画瓢
on Wednesday, okay? And I'll give you a video of the demo,
照着我今天和星期三的视频做一遍
so you'll see it, and you'll be able to watch it. And
没错，我会把视频发给你们
then on Friday, we have an optional section.
星期五的课是选修课，不会放到 iTunes U 上
So the Friday sections in this course,
所以星期五的课
you don't have to go to if you don't want to.
同学们不感兴趣可以不来上
But a lot of times, they're very valuable
但其实这些课程都一般都很有用
feature. So if you have not used the debugger in Xcode 8
所以如果你没有用过 Xcode 8 的调试器
you really might wanna go to Friday's lecture.
我推荐你来听听
The location and time of it will be posted on the class
上课的时间和地点看我之后发的公告
forums hopefully tomorrow. I've asked for the room and
我还在申请上课用的教室
haven't quite got it yet so hopefully tomorrow. And
希望明天能搞定，然后通知你们
then don't forget next Monday is a holiday so we're not
下周一放假，不上课
meeting on Monday. Our next class after this Wednesday
所以再下一次上课是星期三
will be next Wednesday. So let's hop into the demo...
好，我们开始 demo 吧
I said we were gonna build a calculator, let me actually
既然我们要编一个计算器
show you a calculator. This is the macOS calculator and
那我们先来看 macOS 上的计算器
our calculator is gonna look very similar to this, right?
我们的计算器基本会照着这个来做
It has to display along the top, it has the keypad for
最上面是显示，下面是按键
typing numbers in and it's got these operation buttons. And
包括输入数字和执行运算的按钮
then you can just multiply, times eight, you hit equals,
比如我们现在按 乘，8，等于
it does the operation,
它就会计算出来
that's pretty much what our calculator is gonna do.
我们的计算器就是要实现这样的功能
It's not gonna look exactly like this. It's gonna have
我们 app 的界面不会和这个完全一样
a look that's a little more appropriate for a iOS device,
因为我们会在保持界面基本元素的基础上
but it's generally this. And I promised that Xcode would be
为适应 iOS 设备作出些微调
your one-stop shop for doing all development, so
Xcode 无所不能
we're gonna spend our entire time here working in Xcode.
因此我们开发会全程使用 Xcode
Now Xcode is an app that you just go to the Mac App Store,
你可以从 Mac App Store 上免费下载
and you download it. It's free.
请勿从百度云等第三方渠道下载
When you first launch it, it's gonna put up this splash
当你第一次打开它的时候，你可以看到这个
screen like you see right here.
这个欢迎界面
And all of your projects are going to start accumulating
Xcode 会记住你的各个项目
here over on this right side where this gray area is. And
并展示在现在这片灰色的地方
you can basically do three other things here. You can use
这里有三个选项
a playground, which I'll show the playgrounds on Wednesday,
你可以新建一个 playgroud，这我星期三会讲
it's kind of a little play area for iOS programming. You
你可以在 playground 中简单试试自己的代码
can check a existing project out of a source control
你可以添加代码管理源的项目
management system which we're not gonna be doing.
但我们不会讲这个
Although we're probably have a Friday section
也许星期五我们可以
on doing a source code control. So we're gonna be
介绍下源代码管理
doing this option right here, Create a new Xcode project.
我们大部分时候会用这个 Create a new Xcode project
And in fact, when I do demos in this course,
实际上之后所有的 demo
I almost always start from scratch.
我基本都会从零开始
Cuz I don't want you to have to like,
因为我不想为了节约时间
come up to speed on some code that I give you first, and
先编好一部分，发给你们
then, learn from there. So we try to start from scratch, and
你们再以此为基础开始学
see what we can do that way. So I'm gonna click on this,
所以我们会从头开始，不会藏着掖着
to start a new app. It's asking, what kind
好，我们点了这个选项之后，Xcode 会问
of app do we want to build, or what kind of project, and
你想编一个什么样的程序
here you can see, we can do Watch apps, Apple TV apps,
你可以选开发 手表，电视，电脑上的程序
even Mac OS apps, but we're doing iOS, and in fact,
不过我们这门课讲的是开发 iOS 程序
we're always going to choose this Single View Application
所以我们一直会选这个 Single View Application 模版
template. It's the simplest template, and
这是最简单的一个
some of t hese other templates have code in there that I
其它的模版里面都已经帮你把重要的代码写好了
actually want to show you how to write yourself instead of
我们这堂课就是教你们如何
having the template just make that code appear, all right?
不依赖模版就能写出那些代码
So we're gonna do Single View Application.
好，点击 Single View Application
Now it wants some particulars on our application,
然后 Xcode 会让你填些详细信息
most importantly at the top its name. Well,
这里最重要的是 Product Name，项目名称
we're building a calculator so we're gonna call this
既然我们编的是计算器，所以取名叫 Calculator
Calculator, okay, that's gonna be the name of our app.
因为各种原因请使用英文命名
Now this second line here, team, that's the team of
下面这个 Team 是开发团队
developers who are gonna work on this project, that's gonna
指定哪些人会开发这个程序
be a team of one, which is you. Okay, when you launch
当然这里是你自己一个人组成的个人团队
Xcode, this is probably not going to be a pull down list.
当你打开 Xcode 的时候，这里多半不是这样一个下拉列表
It's gonna be a button that says Add Account or
你会看到一个写着 Add Account
something like that, Add Team. You click on that, all you'll
或是 Add Team 一类的按钮。点了那个按钮之后
need is an Apple ID, any Apple ID will do, won't cost you any
你需要登录 Apple ID。如果你没有的话可以去免费注册一个
money. And go through the dialog there and
登录之后
it'll add a team for you, and you use that here. Alright?
你就能在这里看到你的个人团队了
This organization name can be anything you want.
这里的 Organization Name, 组织名称可以随便填
It's just gonna appear on the copyright symbol at the top of
Xcode 会在你每个文件的开头
your source code files, that's it. But this one,
用这个组织名声明版权，仅此而已。但请保证下面这个
it's super important that this be a unique identifier of you.
Organization Identifier，组织标识符是独一无二的
Okay? So I strongly recommend doing edu.stanford.cs193p.
对于斯坦福的学生，我强烈建议使用
You're SUNet ID here, okay? If you put that in there,
edu.stanford.cs193p.你的SUNetID
you're almost guaranteed, if you're a Stanford student,
那至少对于每一个斯坦福学生来说，你不会和别人的重复
for that to be unique. If you're not a Stanford student,
如果你不是斯坦福的学生
you're watching this on iTunes U, pick something else that
也就是在 iTunes U 上观看的
uniquely identifies you. Hopefully,
请自行挑选一个独特的标识符
reverse DNS notation will work in your circumstance as well.
惯例是使用公司／个人网站域名的反写
The language we're gonna use like I said is Swift.
Language，编程语言选 Swift
iOS was originally written in a different language called
在发明 Swift 之前开发 iOS 程序都是使用 Objective-C
Objective-C. Turns out you can use Objective-C and
当然现在也能够在同一个程序中
Swift in the same application.
使用 Swift 和 Objective-C 混编
They use the exact same underlying iOS API. So
这两个语言都使用的是同一个 iOS API
everything you're gonna learn in this class in Swift,
你在这节课中学到的所有有关 Swift 的知识
if you later went and learned Objective-C, all that learning
都能帮助你以后学 Objective-C（如果你想学 OC）
would be valid, okay? Cuz it's the exact, in fact,
因为 Swift 有一部分正是
it's the exact same code base, it's not just same API.
基于 Objective-C 的
Swift was designed in a way to be quite compatible with
Swift 也在设计上尽量兼容 Objective-C
Objective-C's APIs. And in the last couple years,
过去几年中苹果也在
they've even enhanced Objective-C to catch up with
改善 Objective-C，吸收一些
some of the advanced stuff that Swift does. Our app that
Swift 的优点
we're going to build, our calculator is going to
这里的 Device，设备选 Universal，通用
be universal. That means it's going to run on iPhone and
因为我们这个计算器在 iPhone 和 iPad 上都能运行
on iPad. First couple weeks, it will be iPhone only but
虽然前几周我们只会顾及到 iPhone
then, eventually, we'll add iPad support, as well.
之后我们会慢慢加入对 iPad 的支持
We're not gonna be using a database in the calculator,
我们的计算器不需要使用数据库，所以不选择 Use Core Data
but we will in your assignment five. And when it comes to
在之后的第五个作业中我们才会用到
testing, which is super important, again, I'm hoping
Testing，测试是很重要的部分
to have a Friday section to tell you a lot about testing,
我会在星期五的课上讲到
especially the UI testing framework is really awesome,
特别是这个非常好用的 UI 测试框架
okay, so hopefully we'll get a chance to show you that. So
希望我能展示给你们看看
I'm just gonna click next here to create my app.
点击 Next，下一步
It says, where do you wanna put this project? I recommend
Xcode 会问你要把这个项目存在哪里
you put it home directory in a folder called Developer. Okay?
我推荐放在你用户根目录下的 Developer（开发者）文件夹中
Then all your apps will just pile up in here.
所有的项目放在一起方便查找
This is pretty much a canonical place to put it so
大家都约定俗成放在这里
I strongly recommend it. And
我也推荐这样做
then again source control is more for teams working on it.
这里的 Source Control，源码管理主要是针对团队协作
You're gonna be working this by yourself so
你是自己一个人开发
you can leave this switched off.
所以建议不勾选这个
All right, here's our, there's your load.
到此我们就完成了
There's your first iOS app,
创建你的第一个 iOS 程序的步骤
okay? Now let me explain a little bit about Xcode and
我会讲讲 Xcode
how it's laid out here. So if you haven't seen it...
和 Xcode 的界面布局
How many people have worked in Xcode before? See, so
有多少人用过 Xcode 了？
again probably half of you so quite a few. For those of you
有不少呢，差不多有一半的人
who haven't, it's divided into these three main sections
对于那些不了解 Xcode 人，Xcode 界面主要分为三个部分
here. This main section in the middle is the primary place
中间这个主要的部分是工作区
you're going to do all your source code editing and
是用来写代码的
things like that. That's where you do most of your work.
大部分时候你都会使用这个区域
This section over here on the left, this blue section is
左边这个淡蓝色的部分是 Navigator，导航器
called the navigator. You use it to navigate your project.
用来在工程中导航
And here you're seeing it in a file based view,
默认是显示文件导航
where I'm looking at all my files. And we'll look at
你可以看到工程中所有的文件
those in a second. But you can navigate by searching,
你也可以搜索
okay, there's a search panel. If you, if you're debugging,
这是搜索面板
you can navigate through all the break points that you
在调试过程中你可以浏览所有的断点
have, etc. So, you'll learn all about the different
随着学期进展你们会慢慢学会
ways that you can navigate, as the quarter goes on.
每一个部分的具体用法
On the right hand side here you see this little area,
右边这个是
this is called the utilities window.
Utilities, 实用工具区域
And I'm gonna talk all about this in about five minutes,
我马上就会讲到
okay, we're gonna use this in great detail. I want to
讲到时我们再细看这个部分
show you a little bit how you can manage your space here.
你是可以自定义 Xcode 界面布局的
If you look in the upper right you see these buttons here.
右上角这里有三个按钮
You can click this one over here to hide and
点击它们来显示或隐藏对应的部分
show. That utilities window. And same thing over here for
这个对应的实用工具区，这个对应的是导航器
the navigator. So that can make more space for you.
这样你就能有更多的空间了
All right, and there's another one here, this middle.
中间的这个
That hides something from the bottom.
对应的是窗口底部的这个
This is your debugger window on the left and
左边是 debugger window，调试界面
your console, which is a place where you can log
右边是 console，控制台，在调试时
strings out to while you're debugging, on the right. And
用来展示你程序 log，输出的信息。
we'll see that in a moment as well. All right, so
一会儿我们会用到
let's go look at these files, right?
我们再来看看这些文件吧
We're in the file navigator here on the left. And
在左边的文件导航器中
there's six files here but
可以看到有 6 个文件
four of them are really just supporting files, and
其中有 4 个都只是辅助的文件
we're not not even gonna look at them in the calculator.
我们编计算器不需要修改这些
We'll look at a couple of them as the quarter goes on but,
虽然我们以后会用到其中一些
they're not primary files.
总之你不需要太在意它们
And for example, this one Assets.xcassets, Xcode assets.
比如这个 Assets.xcassets，Xcode 素材文件夹
This is images and videos that might be embedded in your app.
需要在项目中使用的图片和视频都放在这里
You can see it's the app icon,
比如这个就是应用的图标
I haven't set any of my app icons, you can see there's a lot of different resolutions of them. But
需要这些不同尺寸的，我还没有设置
this xcassets and the Launch Screen and this Info.plist and
选中 xcassets，Launch Screen，Info.plist，AppDelegate
this AppDelegate here. By the way, I'm pulling down command,
在 macOS 中是按住 command 键多选
you see in the lower left you can see any command keys that
在我屏幕左下角有显示
I press right down there cuz I'm gonna use command keys for
我们要同时操作这几个文件
various things that we do. So
要实现多选
I use command to select all these. And
就要按住 command 键
I'm just gonna right click and
点击鼠标右键／触控板辅助点击
go down to here, New Group From Selection. And it's gonna
选 New Group From Selection
put these four files into their own little folder.
用这些文件新建一个组
There, it did it, I'm gonna call it Supporting Files,
重命名为 Supporting Files
okay. And I can move these around in the navigator.
把这个文件夹移到下面
See there they are, hidden in there. We're not gonna look at
可以看到这些文件都还在那里
those. We're gonna focus in these two files right here,
我们目前只关心这两个文件
okay? This file, is your first look at Swift. Here it is.
ViewController.swift 是你们看到的第一个 Swift 文件
It's got some very important methods right here, which I'm
模板里自带了一个很重要的函数
gonna delete. Okay? They are important, but the fact that
虽然很重要，但我还是要把它删掉
I deleted them doesn't make them not important.
这并不是说这是无关紧要的
It's just that I'm not gonna teach you about them for
只不过是我们几周后
another couple weeks.
才会讲到
So we're not gonna use them in the calculator. And in fact,
我们今天的计算器中不会用到
I'm gonna go into detail about this Swift code more
我们先不着急学 Swift
in a moment. But before I do that,
在我们开始写代码之前
I wanna focus on this file right here, Main.storyboard.
我们先看看 Main.storyboard
This is your user interface. This is calculator's user
这是（计算器的）UI，用户界面
interface. And one thing you notice when I click on that,
可以看到，我们点开之后
there's no code here. When you build your user interface
这里是没有代码的。在编写 iOS 程序的时候
in iOS app in Xcode, you do not write code.
你可以选择不通过代码实现
We're just gonna to build it with the mouse. We're gonna
用鼠标把控件
drag some things out. We're gonna use some inspectors to
拖拽到界面中。还能通过检查器
set the objects we want. The way we want them. That's how
自定义对象的属性。
we're gonna build our UI. That code that you saw.
没错，我们就是这样构建 UI 的。我们要写的代码
That is only gonna control the behavior of the UI.
只是用来实现 UI 背后的逻辑
What happens when you touch on a button? Things like that.
比如我们按下一个按钮后会发生什么一类的
That's what's gonna be controlled by that code. But
那就是我们代码所要实现的
the actual layout of all the buttons and all that stuff.
至于按钮和其它元素的布局
Is gonna be done here in this graphical view.
我们都是通过这个图形界面完成的
Now you can see there's this area here on the left, okay?
左边这个，叫做
This is like, this is called document outline.
Document Outline，文档大纲
If you don't, here you'll see a little button there.
如果你看不见，按下面这里有个小按钮
The document outline. The document outline has
文档大纲就出来了
all the things in the user interface in an outline form.
这个大纲会展示所有用户界面里的内容
And that's gonna be very useful for
之后对我们来说是非常有用的
us. Later in the quarter. So, I'm gonna hide that.
现在我先把它隐藏起来
That's this little button down here is. It hides and
下面这个按钮可以显示／隐藏这个大纲。
shows it. We're gonna hide that to make more space.
收起来之后我我们就有更多的空间了
We're not gonna use that in the calculator either. So
编计算器也不会用到
that leaves this space here in,
现在我们看到的这个区域
if I zoom in on a little bit here,
可以放大
or zoom out rather. You can see I start to see something
可以缩小。现在看起来，
that looks like an iPhone. Okay, it's kinda iPhone
是不是像个 iPhone 呢？像是 iPhone 屏幕的比例
shaped, I can also by the way hold down the option key and
如果我按住 option 键
use my mouse wheel to zoom in here. Okay, so this is like
滚动鼠标中键也能缩放
an iPhone, in particular it looks like an iPhone 7.
中间空白的形状很像 iPhone 7
You see down here at the bottom it says view as iPhone
下面这里写着使用 iPhone 7 预览
7, all right? And if I click on view as iPhone 7,
"view as iPhone 7"，我点击这个
you'll see all the other iOS devices appear- iPads,
会展示其它的 iOS 设备，比如各种 iPad
for example. Or old iPhone 4s, they're really kinda little.
或是老旧的 iPhone 4s，相比之下屏幕要小得多
And not only are they there but you can switch their
不仅能选择不同的设备，还能选择
orientation, okay? Now when you build an iOS app,
屏幕的旋转方向。开发 iOS 程序
you want the UI to look good on all these devices. And
你应该让 UI 在所有设备上都很美观
you don't wanna have to write a lot of special if,
你也不应该用 if...then 来特殊情况特殊处理
then code all over the place to make them work. So, this
才能让 UI 适合不同的尺寸
whole system that, of building our UI, which by the way,
我们用来构建 UI 的这个部分
is call Interface Builder. This part of Xcode is called
在 Xcode 中叫做 Interface Builder（IB）
Interface Builder, is oriented with a lot of functionality
界面编辑器继承了很多功能
to make you, make it so you can build your UI once and
让你能够一次编写
it will work on all these devices. Now, I'm not gonna
处处运行
actually start doing that until the end of the lecture
我会把优化 UI 留到最后
on Wednesday. So, for now, we're just gonna build our UI,
星期三的课再来处理。现在 UI 只需要个大概
it's gonna be kinda a mess. We'll throw buttons anywhere
马马虎虎就行
we want. We're not really, really working in
按钮随便放哪里都行
landscape mode like this vs portrait or small
暂时我们也不需要考虑横屏
device or large device, ok? We're not gonna worry about
或是不同的屏幕大小
that right off the bat but you just wanna preview the fact
不过即使我们现在不需要在意
that we are eventually gonna build this universal UI
不过你们要明白
that works on all of them. So here's our iPhone 7.
最后我们会构建一个通用的 UI。这是我们的 iPhone 7
We wanna start building our UI. What do we need? We need
让我们开始吧。我们需要些什么？
buttons and we need a kinda a display across the top.
我们需要一些按钮，和一个放在上面的显示屏
Let's start with the buttons. Where do we get these buttons?
我们从按钮开始。可是按钮在哪里呢？
Well, as promised. I'm gonna talk about this utilities area
乘此机会讲讲这里的实用工具区域吧
right here. Now, this utilities area has a top and
现在看到实用工具区域分为了上下两个部分
a bottom. You see that? And in the bottom,
对吧？下面的这个部分叫做
right here, under this region called the object library, is
Object Library，对象库
a library of iOS objects that you can build your app out of.
集合了 iOS 开发中各种你需要用到的对象
And it has things like buttons, text fields,
比如按钮，文本字段
it has more complicated things like image views and
也有更复杂的图像视图
text views, which are multi line and editable text ,and it
文本视图，支持多行可编辑的文字
even has things like that map thing I was telling you about.
还有之前说的地图视图
Or a web view, which is basically Safari in a little
或是网页视图，封装在一个长方形里的 Safari
rectangle. So it's got a lot of powerful things and
功能强大的控件数不胜数
there's a lot of them in here. And we will try to cover
这里因有尽有。接下来的半学期我们会
the vast majority of these in the course of the quarter.
学到大部分的使用方法
But it's almost really too much to cover. So
但种类实在是太多了
we're gonna start though simple with a button. And
我们先定一个小目标，从按钮开始
if I want a button in my UI, I just pick it up with
如果我想要一个按钮，我用鼠标选中
the mouse, okay, and drag it in. Now when I drag it in, see
然后拖到设计界面里来。拖到某些位置
these blue lines are trying to help me put it in a good spot.
会出现蓝色参考线引导我
You see that? Now, we're not gonna pay attention to that
这不是今天的重点
right now because I told you we're doing this thing where
界面优化
we're building the app that'll work on all devices. But
我们留到最后
when we start thinking about
制作响应式布局的时候
putting it on an app that works on all devices we
使用这些蓝色参考线
really wanna use these dashed blue lines. Okay, because if
有很大的帮助
you say something like I want this to be in the center.
比如说要把这个按钮居中
Well now it'll be on the center on every device,
这个按钮不论在什么设备上
no matter what this size of the screen, you see? So
都会自动居中
these blue lines help you communicate that to interface
你现在看到的这两条辅助线表示
builder, that you wanna it in the exact center. So again,
这个按钮一定要出现在屏幕正中间
we're not gonna worry about that for now, so
我们目前并不担心界面不好看
I'm just gonna drop this in the middle of nowhere. But
所以我会随便放一个地方
again, those blue lines are gonna be very important down
再次强调，这些蓝色参考线以后会用到
the road. All right so we've got this button here.
好，这个按钮在这里
It's not [LAUGH] a very good button,
并不是很美观（笑）
because it's kinda small and it says button on it.
又小，又写着 Button 在上面
And we want it to be let's say one of our number buttons.
我们更希望这是个写着数字的按键
Okay, so how are we gonna do that?
怎么更改显示的标题呢？
Well, we can double click on it. And
在按钮上双击
type one of our numbers, I'll make this be my 7 button, so
然后输入我们的数字，比如说 7
this is gonna be my 7 button on my calculator. And I can
这就是我们计算器上的数字七了
resize it, you see when I select it I get these handles.
我还可以调整按钮的大小。选中之后会出现这些尺寸控点
So I can just pick it up by a corner and resize it.
我可按住任一尺寸控点，拖动来改变大小
And when I do, it even tells me exactly what size.
拖动时会选中控件实际的大小
So let's pick maybe a size like mm, 64 by 64?
就把尺寸设为设置为 64 x 64 吧
That's a pretty good computer science size can be
这挺符合一门计算机课程的风格
a little tricky then. Do it there, there, there we go.
虽然要做到精确，还真有些困难（汗）
Okay, so we get 64 by 64 now.
好了，调整成 64 x 64 了
Actually the size is not even gonna matter in the long term,
长远来看其实大小并不重要
because on a smaller device like an iPhone 4 it's gonna be
比如像 iPhone 4 这种设备上我们要把尺寸
shrunk down and
缩小
on another device it's gonna be shrunk out. But for now,
大一些的设备上需要放大
will pick some that's kinda using a reasonable amount of
但现在我们还是选一个针对 iPhone 7
the screen real state on an iPhone 7. This is still
比较合理的尺寸
kinda a small seven. We want it larger. So when we wanna do
这个 7 看着有点小，我们稍微把字号调大一些
things like that that's when we go to the top half.
像这样的设置我们看到右边上半部分
I'm just gonna get rid of this bottom half by scrolling it
我把这下面半部分拖下来隐藏到这里
down here. We're gonna the top half of this utilities pane.
我们现在右边这个实用工具区域
And this is inspector and there's different kinds of
有不同的检查器
inspectors. We're gonna be using the attribute inspector
我们要用的是属性检查器
here, but there's also, for example, a size inspector.
这里还有尺寸检查器
And when I click on that, you see that there's the 64 by 64,
我点击之后，你可以看到这里写着 64 x 64
I could have just typed it in instead of trying
我其实可以直接在这里输入数字
to get it exactly on there. Okay. The attributes inspector
设置准确的尺寸。回到正题，属性检查器
is kinda an object oriented inspector.
是面向对象的
You can see that it knows a button is selected, so
它知道我选中了一个按钮
it's showing you button things.
所以显示按钮相关的属性
Things that you can set about a button. But
你能设置按钮的这些属性
a button is a class, object ordinate class that inherits
按钮是一个类，继承了控件
from control, so you're seeing control things, and
所以一个控件的基本设置也出现在这里
that inherits from view, so you're seeing view things.
控件继承自视图，所以视图的设置也在这里
So this inspector is object orientated and
所以检查器是面向对象的
shows you all the things that can be inspected about this
不仅能显示控件本身的属性
object even using inheritance. So if I wanna change something
还能显示继承的属性。要更改按钮的字体大小
like the font, I just look down here, title, here it is.
我只需要在这里找到 Title 下面的
Font. Right here. I'm gonna click on this and
Font，就是这个，点击右边这个
I'm gonna change this to 30 point let's say. Okay.
我把字号调成 30 号
That looks pretty good. Now, maybe I wanna have
看起来还不错。我还想要给按钮
a background for this button. So, if I look in here there's
加个背景色。看看属性选择器，里面有
that background image. I don't want a background image.
Background Image，背景图片
I actually want a background color. So
我们要颜色不是图片
there's nothing in button that does that.
按钮类里面没有
But, If I go down to view. I can see background right here
但是我们在下面 View 这里有一个 Background
that's a color. And if I click on this, I can pick a color,
正好是颜色，点击这里，我可以选择一个颜色
one of these pre-defined colors, or other colors, let
可以是默认的颜色，或者点 Ohter
me choose from Color Picker a little crayon box or whatever.
然后从 macOS 的颜色选择器中选一个颜色
So I'm just gonna pick from here the light gray.
我就选择这个 Light Gray Color
That looks like a good background color. So
浅灰色挺适合当背景的
now I've got a button, okay? Here's a nice button.
现在按钮看起来漂亮多了
In fact, we could even run, see what our app looks like.
其实我们已经能运行下程序，看看效果怎么样了
Just with one button. Now when it comes to running,
虽然只有一个按钮。运行之前
the way you decide where you wanna run your program,
你能决定在什么设备上运行
because you can run it on your device or you can actually run
你可以选择真机调试，也能使用
it on a simulator. Okay, and for the first few weeks in
模拟器（Simulator）。前几周
this class you can use the simulator.
我推荐使用模拟器
Towards the end of the class I'm gonna
之后我会让你们
ask you to start running on your device so
使用你们自己的设备
you get used to doing that as well. But the way you do that
让你们也熟练掌握这个过程。选择设备的方法是
is you go up here. You see it says calculator iPhone 7 Plus.
在这左上角，写着 Calculator > iPhone 7 Plus
If you click on that you'll see a whole
点击这里你能看到
bunch of simulators. These are all simulators of all those
所有的模拟器。这些都是不同能
different devices that can run iOS 10. And then right up at
运行 iOS 10 的设备
the top here, you could pick, if you had an actual device
如果你通过数据线连接了一台 iPhone 或是 iPad
connected to your Mac, you could pick a physical device.
就会出现在这里供你选择
And I'll be showing you that in a couple of weeks,
几周后我会做示范
as well. So, let's run it on iPhone 7, okay,
让我们选择使用 iPhone 7 运行
so I just picked iPhone 7, now I'm going to press this little
点击 iPhone 7，然后点击这个
play button right here to run it. Okay, now it's going to
三角形的按钮开始运行。现在 Xcode 会
launch the simulator. Now that simulator is a full iPhone
启动模拟器。模拟器五脏俱全，几乎和 iPhone 一样
simulator, so it's not just running our app in a window.
所以并不只是在一个窗口中预览我们的程序
Let's go find it here. It's over here, and
我们切换到 Simulator
it's kind of big here, we'll make it small in a second. So,
现在显示的界面太大了，等会儿我们把它缩小点
this, and in fact, there it is. You can see it zoomed in,
我们向上看，能找到放大了的按钮
now the iPhone 7 has very high resolution, and
iPhone 7 的分辨率很高
I'm running on a small resolution screen. But
我的电脑分辨率没那么高，可以通过
you can actually go down here to scale, and scale it
菜单栏中的 Window > Scale 调整
down a bit. Maybe that's too much. Let' scale it to here.
缩小。好像又太小了，我稍微放大些
Yeah. So we're seeing 50% size here of an iPhone 7.
我们现在看到的是 50% 大小的 iPhone 7
And there's our 7 button right there. Okay,
能很容易找到按钮数字 7
now, you can press the Home button
要按下这个 iPhone 的 Home 键
on this iPhone 7 by going to Hardware > Home. And
可以用菜单栏中的 Hardware > Home
when you do that, look. This looks just like an iPhone.
看到了吧，按下去之后和 iPhone 一模一样
You've got settings. You can go in and set some settings.
比如这是系统设置，你可以打开来修改一些设置
Okay? Do home again. Cmd+Shift+H is home.
按下 Command+Shift+H 也是按下 Home 键
And then you can go back to your app,
再回到我们的程序里
which is the calculator right here. So
就是这里的之个 Calculaor
if you're writing an app, for example, that uses GPS and
比方说你写的程序需要使用 GPS 定位
you need to go to the settings to enable GPS location.
你就需要到设置中启用这个功能
You can do that here on your simulator, okay?
模拟器是可以模拟地理位置的
All right, so we got the 7 button, let's click it. Okay,
我们试试点击这个按钮
well, It's flashing, so it looks like it's working, but
点一下会闪一下，好像在工作
of course, it's not doing anything. We haven't told our
当然并不会有其它的什么效果
7 button what to do, so it's doing nothing, all right? So
我们还没告诉按钮 7 应该做什么，所以什么都不会发生
let's go make it do something. Now I told
那我们就来让它干点什么吧
you that the behavior of the UI is written in code. So
我们需要写代码来响应界面的操作
that's what this guy over here is, this ViewController.swift.
这就是 ViewController.swift 的作用
That's the code where we're gonna do the behavior. And so,
里面包含了实现逻辑的代码
how do we hook up this UI to this code? Well to do that,
如何把代码和界面连接起来呢？
we need to get them both on screen at the same time,
我们需要让代码和界面同时显示在屏幕上
all right? And the way we do that is with this button,
我们需要点击这里画着两个圈圈的按钮
right here, assistant editor button.
显示 Assistant Editor
So I'm gonna click it, and we get both. And I can click for
我再点 Storyboard，代码和 UI 就同时出现了
example, on one side to show my UI. And
现在左边显示的是 UI
it's automatically going to show the code on the other
右边会自动显示代码
side. Okay, cuz it already,
因为大多数时候
it knows that I probably wanted to do that. And
我们一般都是要连接两者
it does that because, up here at the top you see it says,
当然右边需要上面这里选中了
automatic. It's automatically picking it. Now you can go to
Automatic，自动选择。或者你也可以调成
manual and manually pick the file you want to appear here,
Manual，手动选择你想要打开的文件
but most of the times you're leave this on automatic. And
通常情况选 Automatic
it's gonna pick automatically the thing that makes the most
Xcode 都能自动选中
sense to be on the right hand side. Okay,
当前最有用的文件
we'll make some more space there. All right? So
我们把工作区调大一点
let's zoom this in a little bit so
同时把 UI 界面也缩小点
we can see the whole iPhone 7,
显示出整个 iPhone 7
all right, so let's look at this code first because this
我们来仔细研究下这个文件
is the first time you've seen Swift.
因为你们都是第一次看到 Swift 代码
Swift is really nice, because it's kind of succinct and
Swift 的优点之一就是简洁
kind of very obvious in the keywords it's chosen, etc. So
使用的关键字也大多都通俗易懂
import is like include in a lot of languages, it's
import 就像是其它语言中的 include
just basically saying I want to use this framework UIKit.
意思就是我想要使用 UIKit 框架
Now, this is our UI behavior controlling code.
因为这是我们控制 UI 界面的代码
So of course, it needs to use UIKit,
UIKit 自然必不可少
okay? If we were to write an object that's more of like
如果我们写的是
the internals of the calculator that's
计算器的逻辑部分
UI independent,
和 UI 毫不相关
then we would probably import foundation here.
那我们更可能是 import Foundation
Foundation to kind of get to that Core Services layer,
Foundation 框架是 Core Services 层的
not UI. You would never want to import UIKit in one of
和 UI 无关。在和 UI 无关的文件中
those non-UI kind of classes. And you'll see that when we do
不要 import UIKit。星期三讲到
the MVC on Wednesday. There's of course other things we can
MVC 的时候你就明白了。盎然我们也能
import too, like map kit, things like that. All right,
import 其它的库，比如 MapKit。
so here you're seeing your first declaration
接下来是你看到第一个类的声明
of a Swift class. Okay? Keyword class, of course.
Swift 里的类理所应当地使用 class 作为关键字
Name, this is the name of the class. ViewController is
这个是类的名字，ViewController
name of class, it's kind of a generic name.
这是一个很笼统的名字
Probably would have given it a better name if I had had
我们最好给它取个更好的名字
a chance, but this is what the template gave me.
但这就是模板中默认的
You can't unfortunately just rename this by typing,
然而改名并不只是在这里改就完事了
because it's linked up to your UI. I will show you how to
因为它已经和 UI 是互相关联的。我之后会教你们
rename this class later. But for now, we're going to stick
怎么正确地改名。现在我们就先凑合用
with this generic name. This colon UI view controller is
这个普通的名字吧。这个 : UIViewController
the class that view controller inherits from, okay? This is
是 ViewController 继承的父类
object oriented programming, this is inheritance.
面向对象不可或缺的继承
Again, you have to know object oriented programming to be
再次强调，理解面向对象
sitting in this room. So you know what that means?
是上本课的前提。所以你应该知道
Swift is single inheritance. So you can only inherit from
Swift 也是单一继承，也就是只继承一个类
one class. And view controller inherits from this class.
ViewController 就只继承自 UIViewController
This class' capabilities are, it knows how to control a UI.
这个类的功能就是控制 UI
That's why it's called a view controller. We call this our
所以叫视图控制器
view over here, and it knows how to control it.
这个类知道如何控制这边的视图
So this view controller is inheriting all the capability
正是继承了父类的所有功能
of how to control this. Which is great,
才让它知道如何控制。那真是挺不错的
because that's exactly what we want it to do. And
因为这正是我们想让它做的
then inside the curly braces, here we're going to put all of
大括号里面是类的主体
our instance variables and methods. Okay?
包括了实例属性和方法
Hopefully everyone knows what an instance variable
希望大家都还记得什么是实例变量
and a method is, right?
什么是实例方法，对吧？
An instance variable is like storage of variables inside of
实例变量就是由实例分配内存的变量
our class, and a method is just a function in there.
方法就是类里的函数
By the way, we call instance variables in Swift properties.
还有，在 Swift 中实例变量叫做属性
So if you hear me saying properties,
如果你听到我说属性
I mean like instance variables. Okay,
我指的就是实例变量
we call methods, methods. So what I really want now
方法还是叫方法。我现在想要的是
is that when this button is touched, I want it to invoke
每当按下这个按钮，我想让它调用
a method in my class, right? I want it to call a method.
这个类里的一个方法
That would be perfect cuz then I could put whatever
这样我就能够把其它我想要执行的代码
code I want in there. And
都放在那个方法里
that's exactly what we're gonna do.
这就是我们要做到
Now the way we link that up is kinda kooky. Here we go, I'm
你绝对猜不到这新奇的连接方法
gonna hold down Ctrl. You see I'm holding Ctrl down there.
按住 Control 键
I'm going to drag from this button into my code,
再点击按钮，然后拖动鼠标到代码这边
okay? This is how I'm gonna connect it. And when I let go,
就是这样连接的。我放开鼠标
it says you wanna make a connection between your UI and
就弹出窗口说，你想要连接 UI 和代码
this code, what kinda connection do you want?
但它们之间具体是什么关系？
And there's really two choices.
这里有两种选项
There's Outlet, that means make a property or
一种是 Outlet，连接为属性
an instance variable that points to this thing, so
也就是作为类的实例变量
I can talk to it. And then there's action,
能进行操作。另一种是 Action
which means make a method, and when the buttons touch,
作为一个方法，当按钮被点击
call this method. Everybody got that?
就调用这个方法。明白了吗？
All right, so here it's asking for the name of this method.
好，这里填方法的名称
I'm going to call this method touchDigit.
我把它叫做 touchDigit
Okay, touchDigit. And this method, it can have arguments,
touchDigit 可以带有多个参数
it could have no arguments, or one argument which is,
也可以不带参数，也可以一个参数
the button sending me this message. Now I need
告诉我按下的是哪个按钮
that argument because I want to have one touch
我需要保留这个参数，因为我要用
digit method that all my buttons set. So I'm going to
一个方法来处理所有的按钮
ask the button who's sending it to me, who are you?
所以我需要知道到底是哪个按钮调用的这个方法
What title, are you the 7 button?
你的标题是什么，是 7
Are you the five button, what are you? So
还是 5？究竟是哪个按钮？
I want that sender. This type right here,
所以我要保留 Sender 这个参数。这里的 Type
it says Any, that's the type of the argument. Very, okay,
说参数的类型是 Any
wake-up if you're taking a nap right now, and when you're
注意了，睡觉的同学们，勾重点了
doing your homework, you cannot leave this to any.
做作业的时候，不能把这个留成 Any
Because we know what kind of thing is sending you this
我们知道只有谁会调用这个方法
message, it's a UIButton, so you're gonna wanna change this
只有 UIButton，所以大家一定要改
Any to UIButton. If you miss that step and
把 Any 改成 UIButton。如果你漏了这一步
when you go in there, your code's all gonna be messed up,
你就彻底搞砸了
because the argument type of the sender is gonna be any,
参数的类型变成了 Any
which it just basically means untyped, almost. So
基本上就是没有指定类型
that's no good. So make sure you change this to UIButton.
为了避免悲剧，一定要改成 UIButton
Now, when we connect this, it creates a method. So
点击 Connect 连接，它会自动添加一个方法
you're getting your first look right here at a Swift method.
我们来看看你定义的第一个 Swift 方法
Now, this is actually not part of Swift, okay.
@IBAction 并不是 Swift 的一部分
This is something Xcode drops in there. And it does it so
这是 Xcode 的标记，为了
that it can put this little circle in the gutter.
在左边显示个小圆点
You see that circle right there?
看到这个圆圈了嘛？
If I mouse over that circle, look what happens.
你把鼠标悬停在上面，看看会发生什么
I didn't click on it, I just put my mouse over it. You see,
不需要点击，移过去就可以了
it tells me what this method is hooked up to.
它会显示这个方法和谁建立了连接
In other words, what user interface element sends me
也就是哪些 UI 控件会调用这个方法
this message, okay? So this is purely not a Swift thing,
所以这并不是 Swift 语言的一部分
this is purely an Xcode thing. So this is a Swift method,
这只是 Xcode 的标记。剩下的部分就是方法了
okay? So let's look at the parts of a Swift method,
我分析下 Swift 方法不同的部分
the syntax of it, so you understand a little better.
你们好理解 Swift 函数的语法
And I'm gonna use a different method that I'm just going to
为此我另外写一个方法
make up for this. Let's say I had some
选一个更好的例子，比方说
function called a drawHorizontalLine and
drawHorizontalLine，画一条横线
it draws from some starting position,
从某个起点
which would be a Double to some ending position,
一个 Double 类型的小数，到某个终点
which also be a Double. And maybe it does it using
又一个 Double。也许还使用
some color, which would be a UIColor. Okay? So
某种颜色，类型是 UIColor
there's an example of a Swift method. Notice that it,
这是另一个 Swift 方法的例子
this has three parameters. You see? This one, this one and
它有三个形参，startX，endX，color
this one. This ": Double" is the type of this parameter.
: Double 是这个参数的类型
So it's a double-precision floating-point number. That's
双精度浮点型小数
the type of that parameter. This one's also Double.
这就是这个参数的类型。这也是 Double
This one is a UIColor. Okay, which is a different type.
这个是另一种类型，UIColor
Now what's really interesting about parameters is that you
有趣的是每个参数
have two names for each one. See, from startX,
都有两个名字。from startX
to endX, using a color, each one has two, so what
to endX，using color。什么鬼？
the heck is going on there with those two? Well this one,
怎么会有两个名字呢？前面的这个
the first one, is the external name of this parameter. And
第一个是函数外部的实参标签（argument label）
this is the internal name. So these internal names,
第二个是函数内部的形参名称（parameter name）
like startX, endX, and
就是 startX，endX 和 color
color. You would use those in your code inside this method.
这些名称是在函数里使用的名称
Like, I might say, distance = endX - startX, or
比如 distance = endX - startX
something like that. See I'm using endX and startX
或是其它的。可以看出我在实现函数时
inside this method, right? Part of it's implementation.
用的是 endX 和 startX，对吧？
These external names are used by the callers,
调用函数时则使用这些外部的名称
the people who call this method. So I'm gonna call this
那些调用的人用的实参标签
method from touchDigit here, drawHorizontalLine.
比如我在 touchDigit 中使用  drawHorizontalLine
Now, by the way, Xcode loves to type for you.
Xcode 没崩溃时会帮你自动补全
So I just type drawH and now I'm hitting tab. And tab, and
我只打了 drawH，再按 tab 键，再按一下
it's not only filling out drawHorizontalLine,
Xcode 帮我输入了整个 drawHorizontalLine
but it's showing me all the arguments and
并显示所有要填的参数
tabbing to the first one so I can type it. So notice that
而且已经帮我定为到第一个参数这里了
when it said that, the from, the to, and the using
就像我刚才说的，from，to 和 using
were put in there for me. So if I say from 5.0 to 8.5 using
出现在了这里。如果我说从 5.0 画横线到 8.5
the color UIColor.blue let's say, okay?
使用的是 UIColor 的蓝色
These from and to and using are what the caller uses.
from，to 和 using 是调用这个方法时用的
Notice also, that these things are mandatory. They have to go
而且是必须要用
in here. You can not call drawHorizontalLine like this,
你不能像这样调用 drawHorizontalLine
drawHorizontalLine 5.0, this would be, look like most other
drawHorizontalLine(5.0, 8.5, .blue)
languages, you know, blue. You can't call it like that.
这是行不通的
You have to put these external names in there.
这些标签是必不可少的
Also notice that the external names are picked so
选择标签的时候要尽量保证行文通畅
this reads like English. Draw a horizontal line from 5.0
读起来像英文 —— 画一横条线自 5.0 到 8.5，要使用蓝色
to 8.5 using blue, okay? Swift endeavors
在 API Design Guidelines 中
to be as kind of conversational in the language
Swift 强烈建议让代码
of English as it can be. So
接近自然语言
that's kinda crash course. You're gonna be reading, your
这只是简单的介绍。我给你们的
reading assignment's gonna tell you more about that, but
阅读作业里有更详细的解释
that's the crash course. But now let's take a look at thi-,
但最基础的就这些。好，我们看看
by the way, if your function returns something,
等等，忘了讲了，如果函数或方法有返回值
you just go like this, okay? -> String. It's kind of like,
你就像这样写，-> String
the arrow is saying, out of this comes a String, okay?
这箭头就像是在说，这东西会生成一个字符串
So this would be the return value, okay?
所以也就被作为了表示返回值类型的语法
All right, now, let's look at touchDigit though,
回到正题，touchDigit
touchDigit is weird. Look at its two things here, okay?
touchDigit 有些与众不同，它也有两个参数
The external one is _, okay?
不过第一个是 _，下划线
So does that mean I call it by saying, touchDigit_:
难道我要这样写么？touchDigit(_:
whatever? No, underbar means there is no external. So
并不是。下划线表示不需要标签
you would call touchDigit by just saying,
也就是你只需要写
touchDigit(someButton) cuz that's the argument,
touchDigit(某个按钮) 就行了
it's a button or whatever. Okay, there's no, you won't,
只需要写某个按钮，你并不需要写个
you don't put anything in here, it's not like a foo.
你并不需要写任何的东西。如果这里是 foo
If we had this it would be foo, okay?
那我们这里也要写 foo
That's not in there. Instead, it's this underbar, so
既然不是 foo 而是下划线
you have nothing. Okay? Now, why do we sometimes have
就什么都不写。为什么会有这种情况呢？
nothing? Because sometimes, it's implicit in either
这种情况标签多半存在于
the name of the function or the type of the argument,
函数名或是参数类型里面了
what you're supposed to pass, so you don't need that little
你传入的参数多半包含了，所以不需要
thing. By the way underbar, we almost never use that for
补充说明。下划线一般最多只用在第一个参数的标签
the second, third, or fourth argument.
不会用在第二个，第三个，第四个等等
It's occasionally used for the first argument, not always,
第一个会用，但也不是都会用
occasionally. But never for second, third, fourth, fifth,
第一个偶尔会，但绝对不会用为之后参数的标签
okay? Or next to never. Now in your reading assignment,
出现的概率很小很小。你们的阅读作业是
I'm also going to have you read a document that explains
阅读 Swift API Design Guidelines
how to do this naming. What the rules are,
如何命名，有哪些规则
when do you use an underbar,
什么时候用下划线
when don't you. You're gonna wanna master that document by
什么时候不用。如果你想成为专业的 iOS 开发者
the end of the quarter if you wanna call yourself
你最好在这学期结束前
a professional iOS developer, okay?
掌握并熟练运用这个文档中的规则
It's key to understand that. But this touchDigit, okay, so
非常重要。针对 touchDigit
this function, okay methods, I, just to be clear, methods,
这个函数，好吧，这个方法，准确的说叫方法
we use the keyword func. Okay, cuz it's
虽然我们用的关键字是 func[tion]，函数
a function on a class. This is the name. Parameters go
方法是在类里的函数。这是方法的名字
in parentheses like this, they can be separated by commas if
参数像这样放到小括号里，如果有多个
we have multiple of them. This is the first parameter here,
就用英文逗号隔开。这是第一个参数
first and only. It's type is a UIButton because of course,
有且仅有的一个。参数类型为 UIButton 显而易见的，
a UIButton is sending this messa-, method. Right,
是 UIButton 发起的事件
it's invoking this method. So the sender is this UIButton.
在调用这个方法，所以是 UIButton 类型
And sender is the internal name.
sender 是参数名称
So that's the name we'll use inside here to access it.
方法内部称呼调用的按钮的名称
All right? But before we start doing that, let's just
好，我们正式开始前
have this do something simple like print out to the console.
先做点简单的，比如输出到控制台
So I'm gonna say, print("touchDigit was called"),
print("touchDigit was called")
okay? We're just gonna print that out on the console.
就把这个字符串打印到控制台
Whenever someone touches a button,
当按下按钮
it's gonna evoke this method.
就调用这个方法
It's gonna print that on the console.
然后把这条信息打印到控制台
So let's just do that.
就这样按 Command+R 运行看看
All right? So there's our UI, iPhone 7. Click and touchDigit
iPhone 7 模拟器出来了，按下按钮
appears in the console down here at the bottom, okay?
touchDigit 里这个字符串就出现在下面控制台这里了
Now the console shares space with the debugger,
现在控制台和调试器共享空间
this area on the left is the debugger. So you can kind of
没错，左边是调试器
separate this space back and forth, you can also completely
你可以左右拖动这条分割线
hide this space by using these buttons right here, okay?
或者是用右边这个按钮把它隐藏起来
So we'll just do console only right here. Let's go back to
只显示控制台
our simulator. And so every time we press this,
回到模拟器中，每次我按这个按钮
we get touchDigit was called printed out again.
touchDigit 就会再被调用，然后再打印一次
Does everyone understand what's happening here,
大家都还跟的上吧？刚刚我讲了什么
how we've hooked up this method to the button? Really,
怎么关连 UI 和代码的，
really straightforward. All right, now that we have that
应该都挺好理解的。
working, we know we need more than just this one button,
证明 touchDigit 有用了，还有很多按钮需要加
we need a whole keypad's worth of buttons. So I'm gonna,
我们需要整个数字键盘的按钮
I want these other buttons to look exactly the same, so
我想这些按钮的形状一模一样
I'm gonna copy and paste. So I just copied and pasted that,
所以我们复制粘贴。我复制这个，粘贴
paste another one here. I can even select three at a time,
再来一个。选中这三个按钮
and copy and paste, okay? Paste another one.
再复制粘贴，再粘贴
Now notice here I'm using the blue lines to line them up
稍微注意下，我在用蓝色参考线辅助我
okay, really nicely. Blue lines are great for
对的很整齐。这就是蓝色参考线的用法
doing that. Okay, and now I can just rename these buttons
现在我们只需要给这些按钮改下标题
by just double-clicking on them.
在上面双击，然后修改
All right, so I've got an, a beautiful keypad right here.
这样整洁的数字键盘就做好了
And what's really great is that this method is hooked up
更好的是这个方法和所有的按钮都有连接
to all of them. Okay, that's because when you copy and
因为我们复制粘贴的时候
paste a button, it keeps it's connections to any methods
也会保留按钮的各种连接
that it has, okay? So that's cool. So
这挺不错的
now all these buttons are going to send this touchDigit.
所有的这些按钮都会调用 touchDigit
So now if I run, you'll see that if I press any of
我们现在运行，按哪一个按钮都行
these buttons, not just our 7 button. Right, here's 7,
不仅是数字 7。我们先确认 7 还能用
that worked, but also 5, 0, they're all calling,
很好；我再试试 5，0，也都会
this touchDigit was called. Okay, so that's awesome.
调用 touchDigit。真不错
But of course, we want to know which button was called,
下一步，是找出究竟是
was sending us this message, right?
哪个按钮 send，发送了消息呢？
And we know that because that's the argument,
我们这个参数不正好是 sender 吗？
is the sender, okay? So let's add a local variable here.
所以我们创建一个局部变量
So now you're seeing your local variables in Swift for
啊哈，你们又能学到用 Swift 定义变量了
the first time. It looks like this, var digit, okay?
就像这样，var digit
Var means this is a local variable. Digit is the name.
var 是声明变量的关键字，digit 是变量的名字
Now if we wanted to type it, we could put a type here like
如果我们想的话，可以在这里声明变量的类型
maybe type string. Just like we put a type of our parameter
比如字符串类型，就像声明参数类型差不多
here, we can put a type right here of our local variable.
在变量名字后加 : String
But, we don't usually do that in Swift because while Swift
然而我们一般不需要这样做
is very strongly typed language, in other words,
虽然 Swift 是强类型的语言
you have to specify the types of everything.
也就是每个变量的类型都是确定的
It wants to know the types of everything.
Swift 想知道所有东西的类型
it will infer what type you want from the context.
但大多数时候它都能根据上下文
Very often. Ok? So that's the trade off,
进行类型推导。 这就是 Swift 的权衡
if you have a really strongly typed language, you have
强类型语言，要求所有的都明确类型
to type everything. It's really nice if the compiler
同时提供一个强大的编译器
will just figure out for you what the types of things are.
能通过类型推导来自动判断类型
So, normally, we will leave the types off wherever we can.
所以我们一般能省略就不写
Now, we can't do that in
函数的参数又不同了
a method parameter because we got to know what That method
函数和方法的参数是我们自己决定的
is expecting. But for local variables, we definitely can
但对于局部变量
leave it off almost all the time, okay? So we got this
大部分时候都是可以省略声明类型的
digit, and I just wanna set it equal to something.
有了这个 digit，我想给它赋值
What does it wanna be equal to?
但是如何获得这个 digit 呢？
It wants to be equal to the title of the button
digit 等于引发事件
that's sending me the message. So this guy,
按钮的标题。而 sender
which is a button I want to ask what its title is.
正是这个按钮
Now, how do you send a message to another object in Swift?
Swift 中如何发送消息给对象呢？
Well, you just type the object you want to
你输入那个对象的名称
send the message to and you press dot. Okay, so this is
然后使用点语法，按下英文句号 .
like Java and a lot of other languages, just the object and
这和 Java 以及其它许多编程语言类似
dot, that's how you send the message. Now, unfortunately,
对象.，就是这样发送消息。虽然 Xcode 有自动补全
Xcode is helping me here by showing me all the methods And
然而不幸的是，它把所有按钮的
properties that button can do. Look at this list,
属性和方法都列举了出来。看看这一长串
I'm only in the Fs, okay, I'm still scrolling,
我才滑倒 F 开头的，下面还有
still scrolling. There's a lot of methods. It's like how am I
这么多函数和属性
ever gonna figure out. I just want the title of the button,
我能怎么办？我明明只是想要按钮的标题啊
please. Okay, well, of course I could get the documentation,
当然，我也许可以找到文档
start reading through it,
开始挨个看
trying to figure out, and
看是哪个函数还是属性
in fact I want to do that eventually.
我确实会这么做
there's kind of trick here in Xcode.
不过是靠一个使用 Xcode 的技巧
Which is, just type the name of thing you want,
那就是输入你想要的东西的名称
Type what you think it might be and see what happens.
输入你觉得最可能的名称看看
So, I'm going to type Title. Now there's no method or
我会输入 title，虽然我知道按钮这个类
property in button called title.
并没有叫做 title 的方法或属性
But you can see that Xcode has showed me all the methods and
但是 Xcode 会筛选出一些方法和属性
properties that start with the word title Or
要么是由 title 开头的
that have the word title in it. Or even that have "t",
要么是名称中包含 title 的
"it", "le" in it, okay? So it's doing everything it
甚至还有包含 t，it 和 le 的
can to show you every possible thing that might match what
展示出所有可能搭配上你输入内容的来
you typed. Now, let's look through these and see if we
现在我们再来选择
can find one that will give us the title of the button, okay?
看看有没有能给我们标题的
Title label That doesn't look very good. How about title for
titleLabel，展示标题的标签，好像并不是我们想要的
control state, that looks good,
那 title(for: UIControlState) 呢？
returns the title associated with the specified state.
好像不错，返回和按钮在给出状态下的标题
Mm, that looks pretty good but let's keep looking because I
虽然看起来不错
don't really know anything about the state,
但我对这个状态一无所知
that looks pretty good, but let's keep going.
我们再看看有没有更好的
No edge insets, no, add color, no, shadow, no. Current title,
不是留边，不是颜色，不是阴影。currentTitle
the current title that
当前按钮
is displayed on the button,
显示的标题
victory that sounded exactly what I want. So
就决定是你了
I'm just gonna pick that by double-clicking on it.
我决定就选这个，在上面双击
So I'm just gonna double-click on it. There it is,
双击之后就出现了
it filled it out. And so now we're sending currentTitle
Xcode 帮我输入了。这样我们就得到了 sender
to sender. Now let's find out more about currentTitle, okay?
的 currentTitle。我们再仔细了解下 currentTitle
We know that one-liner that is the current title displayed.
我们知道简介说的是现在显示的标题
I'm gonna hold down Option.
按下 Option 键
See Option down here on the left, okay?
我屏幕左下角显示我按下了 Option 键
I'm gonna hold down Option, and look.
按住 Option 键的同时
When I do Option things that I mouse over turn blue
把鼠标悬浮在这些名称上时
with a little dashed underline.
会变蓝，还有下划线
And if I click, I get a little help, okay? So
我点下去，就会弹出快速帮助
I'm getting that current title display from the button,
除了说这是当前按钮展示的标题
but I'm also getting more detailed description and
还有更详细的解释
I'm getting the declaration of this thing. And
以及它的定义
you could see that this is not a func.
你会发现这不是一个 func，方法
This is a var. So now you're seeing for the first time,
这是一个 var，属性。你们第一次看到
the declaration of a property in Swift, okay?
Swift 中属性的定义吧？
An instance variable. So this is an instance variable,
这就是个实例变量
in UIButton, okay? Called var, makes sense, right?
UIButton 类的一个实例变量
It's a variable, var. It's called currentTitle,
用 var 关键字声明，叫做 currentTitle 的变量
of course. It's type is, string?
类型是 String?
Not sure, maybe button's not sure what the type is.
难道按钮不确定类型是不是字符串？
No, I think button knows but,
我认为按钮是知道的
we're just gonna assume this is string, for now. And
我们暂时当是字符串好了
we'll see, where that takes us. Also notice this little
看看会给我们带来什么麻烦。注意这里的
syntax means that, you can only get the current title,
不起眼的语法，告诉你 currentTitle 是只读的
with this property. You can't set the current title. Now,
你并不能通过这个来更改 currentTitle
what if I was like, well I'm interested. How would I set
如果我就想要更改按钮的标题呢？
the current title? So you would want to, let's say,
如何设置当前的标题？
go look in the documentation. How would you get there?
你会想要查文档。文档在哪里？
Well, if you look down at the bottom, it says more.
这下面有个 More
This property reference right here. If you click on that,
点这个 Property Reference
it brings up the documentation. Okay?
文档就出现了
And here's the documentation for currentTitle. Now what's
currentTitle 的文档
cool about this, is from here, I can click on things.
有趣的是，我可以点击许多的东西
Like String, I could find out about String. Or, look,
比如 String，了解字符串类
I can click on the class that this is defined in, UIButton.
我可以点击定义这个属性的类，UIButton
And here's the UIButton, and look at this section at
这就是 UIButton 的文档
the start of UIButton called Overview. These are awesome,
文档开始这个部分，Overview，概览很有用
and I strongly recommend every class you go to use
我建议每个用到的类
take the five minutes or
都花个五分钟，最多是十分钟
ten minutes at the most to read through these overviews.
认真阅读它的概览
Then you'll really understand how these classes work.
然后你就能理解怎么使用这些类了
Look at this thing. It tells us for
比如这个，给我举例说明
example how to configure the button's appearance.
如何设置按钮的外观
It tells us all about this button's stage.
这个告诉我们按钮的状态
Remember, we had that title for state.
之前看到的 button(for: UIControlState)
And we didn't really know what the state was. Well,
我们不清楚按钮的状态是什么
this tells us about that. Tells you about the content of
这里就给出了解释。这个讲按钮的内容
a button. And you can put an image on there, evidently, and
看来你可以放图片和文字
text. Those edge insets, whatever those are, explained.
留边的解释
Even an interface builder, all those things in the inspector.
甚至还包括界面编辑器，在检查器中出现的
Look, those are all explained, in detail.
这些都详细地解释了
So this is a great thing to just read through this,
阅读这个受益匪浅
understand this for all the common classes. And
最好把常用类的概览都理解了
of course, all of the methods are listed here as well. For
当然，所有能用的方法也列出来了
example, look at this one,
比如看看这个
setTitle. Hm, that might be a way to set the title. And
setTitle，也许可以用来设置标题
if I click on that, I get a full description of this. And
如果我点击这个，就会转到更详细的解释
I even see that the state thing is here, so I can click
这里还有那个 UIControlState
on that. And now I can see the control state, of course,
我点击之后就到了 UIControlState 的文档
there's normal, highlighted button, disabled button,
这里有 正常，高亮，禁用和选中
a selected button. They can each have their own title,
不同的状态可以有不同的标题
cool. But you see how I'm navigating by just clicking
学会我是怎么通过点击来浏览
through the various types and
这些不同的类型的了？
all that you really want to get faster with doing that
你最好尽快掌握
okay it's really important to be a good iOS developer to be
成为好的 iOS 开发者
able to use the documentation effectively. All right, so
高效地使用文档是不可获取的技能
we're back here, we got this thing currentTitle. It's this
好，回到 currentTitle
type string question mark. And I told you that swift would
它的类型是 String?。我说过 Swift
infer the type. And sure enough, look, a digit. It's
能推测类型。那好吧，这是个数字
type is string question mark. Of course, because I just set
类型也是 String?，因为我把一个
it equal to something that was string question mark, so
String? 类型的值符给了它
it knows it's string question mark. So, let's go ahead and
所以 digit 也是 String? 类型的
print this digit out. Okay,
我把这个 digit 打印出来
it's saying touch digit was called. Let's try and print it
把这个 touch digit was called 改成 digit
out. Now in another language, you might use printf.
在其它语言中你可能用 printf
And you might say something like %s was touched.
然后写 "%s was touched"
And then you would put digit right here,
最后把 digit 写着这里
okay? Now unfortunately, you can't do this in Swift, okay?
然而，Swift 里并不是这样操作的
There's no percent s business, okay? And no printf. Instead,
不需要使用 %s 那些，当然也没有 printf
we still say print, okay? But, instead of doing percent s.
我们用 print 就够了。取代 %s 的是
We can actually use the very magical \() parentheses.
神奇的 \()
If you put that inside a string,
如果放在在字符串中
then you can put anything you want inside there that can
括号之间可以放任何
be converted to a string. And
能用字符串表示的内容
it will include it there. Including,
并且插入到字符串中间
a string itself. Can obviously be converted to a string. So
字符串本身当然能用字符串表示
this way, you can embed strings in other strings.
这就是在字符串中插入字符串的方法
Or even embed more complicated objects that know how to turn
我们也能在字符串中插入更复杂的对象
themselves into a string, into strings. Okay, so this is how
只要它们知道怎么用字符串表示它们本身
you do the printf business of printing things out. Okay,
这就是取代 printf 的方法
now also I notice, we have a warning. This yellow thing is
但注意到这里有个警告，这个黄色的
a warning, okay? And they can be yellow which are warnings
可以黄色的，只是警告
in which case it'll compile and run. But, you still got to
可以编译，可以运行。但你不能不改
fix it cuz you cannot submit any homework in this class
这节课交的作业不能有警告
with warnings. You hear me? Or they can be red.
清楚了吗？更不能有红色的
In red's case, it won't even build. So this one's yellow.
那就是有错误，连编译都不行。这里还只是警告
How do we find out what it is? Well, we just click on it.
怎么才知道是什么原因呢？点击一下
When we click on it, it says here the variable digit
点了之后说 Variable 'digit' was never mutated
was never mutated. Means it was never changed.
意思是变量 digit 没有被更改过
Consider changing to let constant, it says. Okay? And
consider changing to 'let' constant，建议改用常量
you can see it even saying do you want me to fix it? I can
它甚至还问是否想要解决这个问题？
replace var with let and it's even showing what that would
说我能帮你把 var 改成 let，还给出了预览
look like to replace var with let. How helpful of it. So
把 var 替换成 let。多省心！
actually, I'm gonna have to do that. I'm gonna click,
那就让它改吧。点击确认
change it to let, warning gone. Now what is all that
改成了 let，警告也没了。不过为啥要这样做？
about? It said digit was never mutated, it was never changed,
既然 digit 没有被修改过
okay? So digit essentially was a constant.
那它就是个常量
We gave it an initial value. It never got changed.
除了我们给它的初始值以外就没变过
When you declare a constant you always want to use let.
定义常量使用 let 关键字
Now why do we have a different word for a constant than for
为什么常量和变量的名称不同呢？
a var? Well, because a constant isn't var.
因为常量不仅是变量
It doesn't vary, a constant is constant.
它不会改变，常量就是常量
And let is a great word because read this. Let digit
let 这个关键字选的很好。连起来读很通顺
equal sender's current title. Okay, reads really nice.
让 digit 等于调用函数的按钮现在的标题
Now why do we care about distinguishing these two?
区分常量和变量的原因归根到底是为什么？
Two reasons. One if you're a reader of someone's code and
两个原因。如果你读其它人的代码
you see let you know that this is not going to change, okay.
看到 let 就知道这是个常量
You know the digit is going to be, never going to change.
知道这个 digit 一定不会变
And in fact if someone did change it or
即使有人修改了
if you tried to change someone else's code and change it,
或者你尝试修改别人代码里的常量
compiler's gonna generate an error, okay. You can't change
编译器就会报错，说你不能修改
something that's constant. But even more importantly,
那是个常量。第二个更重要的原因是
it tells Swift that it's a constant and
它告诉 Swift 这是个常量
that you intend it to be a constant. And so later,
你希望这是个常量。之后
if you try to modify it, even if it's an array or
如果你尝试修改它，对于数组和字典也是
a dictionary and you're trying to put something in the array
如果你尝试向数组添加一个项
Okay? Or add something to the dictionary.
或是给字典添加一对键值
It knows, you intended that to be a constant. So,
Swift 知道你希望那是个常量
you know, error. So it's a way to tell Swift what you intend.
于是会告诉你出错了。所以 let 是为了告诉 Swift 你的意图。
Now, the difference between a mutable array,
数组分两种，可变和不可变
an array that you can add stuff to, and
你可以向可变的数组添加项
an immutable one, is huge. Because if you pa, arrays and
数组占的空间很大。Swift 中
Swift are passed around by copy. Arrays are passed by
数组是通过拷贝来实现值传递，
copy. It's very unusual compared to other languages
传递数组就是复制数组的过程
where an array would just be an object in the heap and
而不是像其它的语言那样
you just pass a pointer to it. You were passing them it
只是传递一个指向数组的指针
copies them every time you pass them to a function.
Swift 中每次把数组传递到函数都会要求复制
Now that'd be very inefficient if they were all mutable. Cuz
如果这些数组都是可变的，那会非常低效
you have to actually copy them in case someone changed it.
因为一旦发生更改，就必须要实际拷贝
But Swift knows which ones are mutable and which aren't.
Swift 知道数组是否可变
And when you pass an immutable one it only- But
如果你传入的是一个只读数组
doesn't really efficient copy, okay,
Swift 会采取更高效的方法
it doesn't actually copy the element. And in fact, until
并不会真的拷贝数组里的项
you assigned it to a mutable variable by saying var equals
直到你把这个数组赋值给一个变量之前
that, it doesn't even have to worry about that. And then it
Swift 都不需要考虑拷贝的问题
can just do copy on write when you actually change it. Okay,
而且就算拷贝也会采取写时拷贝（copy on write）的机制
so that's the var/let thing, get used to it,
你们要习惯区别使用 var 和 let
always do let for constants. All right, so let's run
常量一定要用 let。好，我们现在运行
this now. See what's going on here. This should work, right?
看看什么情况，希望能够运行
We're getting the current title. We're saying, it,
我们获得了按钮当前的标题，然后打印
well, whatever that title was was touched.
某某按钮被按下了
This should be good to go. Here we go. Seven. What?
应该没问题。我试试，按下 7。怎么回事？
Okay, well, it's kinda working.
好吧，算是能用
I mean it's definitely doing something different And
每个按钮按下去打印的内容都不一样
it kinda knows which button.
而且我们也算是出现了相应的标题
But what's all this optional quote business?
但是为什么会有 Optional("") 呢？
What's that about? >> Well, that's because
这是什么造成的？
digit is not a string, it's a string?, okay.
这是因为 digit 不是字符串，是 String?
So what is String? String? is a totally different type
那什么是 String? 呢？String? 和普通字符串
from String. It's called an optional. Alright? This
根本不一样。它的类型叫做可选（Optional）
is super important. So again, wake up if you're napping.
这是重点，睡觉的同学可以起来看看了
Okay? This is super important. Very few languages have this
很重要很重要很重要。很少有编程语言
concept. It's a great concept. It really makes the API really
有这个概念。这是个很不错的概念。这让整个
understandable throughout all of iOS. But it takes a little
iOS API 通俗易懂，但是要求
bit of getting used to, okay? So what is this type optional?
你要适应它。那可选类型是什么？
A type optional has only two values, set and
可选类型的值只有两种情况 —— 有值，或缺省值
not set, okay? That's the only two values it has.
只会有这两种情况
There's no other values. However, when it's in the set
不可能是其它的值。当可选类型的为有值的时候
case, it can have an associated value. Okay?
它会有一个关联值
A value that it kinda keeps on the side and
另一个和这个可选一起存储的值
you specify when you create the optional or
你需要在定义可选类型的时候
you declare it what type that associated value is.
声明关联值的类型
So this, the associated value is a string.
我们这里，关联值的类型就是字符串
We're talking about the title of a button, of course. So
当然了，我说的是按钮的标题
we would say the type
我们把这个 digit 的类型
of this digit is optional String. Which means
叫做 Optional String，可选字符串
an optional who's associative value in the set state is
一个在有值状态下关联值为字符串的可选类型
a string. Okay? Now, in this case that's all fine and
我们现在的情况是一定会有值
good but we want the associated value here.
但我只想要这个关联值
Give me that associated value, that title, okay?
我只要那个标题就可以了
How do I get it out of here? And the answer for
怎么才能解析出这个值呢？最简单的方法
that is exclamation point. Okay, if you put
后面加一个英文叹号 !
the explanation point at the end of an optional then it
如果你在可选类型的后面加上叹号
will, if it's in the set state, grab the associated value and
在可选类型有值的情况下，隐式解析出关联值
give it to you. So now look at the type of digit.
然后返还给你。我们再看看 digit 的类型
It's a string. Okay, Swift is able to infer that since you
太好了，只是普通的字符串了。Swift 如此推测的原因是
unwrapped this optional right here. You've got a string over
你已经把可选类型强制解包了，所以你会得到一个字符串
here. Now what if you do exclamation point and
但是如果你在可选类型的后面加了一个叹号
that optional is in the not set state? Because
但是这个可选类型却缺省值呢？
there's no associated value when it's in not state, that's
因为在缺省值的时候是没有关连值的
only when it's in associated. What happens to your app?
只有在有值的时候才存在关联值。强制解包会发生什么呢？
Anyone want to guess what happens? Crashes. Okay?
猜猜会发生什么？你的程序会崩溃
Kaboom. Now, I'm sure some of you conservative
你的程序就炸了。我知道你们之中肯定有些保守派的
folk out there are like, okay well that's it for
现在在想，好吧我受够了
me, an exclamation point! I'm never using that.
我绝对不会用感叹号的
I don't want my app to crash, that's horrible.
人家才不想让程序崩溃呢，吓死宝宝了
But actually having your app crash during development
但其实在开发过程的时候程序就崩溃了是好事
can be great, because you'll find bugs really
因为你能够尽早发现 bug
fast and you'll be dropped right into the debugger
然后你会被马上带到调试界面
where the crash happened so you can figure whats going on.
告诉你哪里导致了崩溃，让你能理清楚
How could this have happened?
到底是怎么崩溃的
So in this case were talking about the title of a button,
如果我们这个情况下会缺省值
that means the title of the button was never set and
那就是这个按钮并没有标题
this is touch digit. That should never have happen. Okay
这个函数是我们按了数字，按钮没有标题不应该发生
if that happened in something I shipped to my customer,
如果按钮没有标题软件就卖给了客户
customers would be complaining left, right and center.
客户一定会彻头彻尾地批评这个软件
There's a button that has no title on it,
这里有个按钮，标题上什么也没写
nothing on it and I click what,
点下去之后就崩溃
you know what I'm saying?
懂我是什么意思了吗？
So, you want to find those in development.
所以你希望在开发阶段就能发现这些问题
So crashing can be good sometimes.
所以崩溃有的时候是好事情
Now of course you don't always want to crash when you unwrap
当然你并应该每次解包可选类型的时候都导致崩溃
an optional and I'll show you in a little bit how to unwrap
我还会再讲讲如何解包
an optional and get it to associated value. But test it
获取可选类型的关联值
first to make sure that it's in the set state. Okay, but
正常情况下都应该确认可选类型是否有值
for now we do this. Let's run and see what this looks like.
暂时我们先这样吧，先运行代码看看现在是什么情况
It should work. Now we've unwrapped this thing,
应该没有问题了，我们已经解包了这个可选变量
grabbed its associate value.
得到了关联值
And we know the current title should always be set so
而且我们知道按钮的标题是一定存在的
we'll not have to worry about crashing here. And
应该不用担心会崩溃
sure enough seven was touched, nine, whatever, three,
好，7 was touched，9，6，3
five, six, okay? All right, so we're rocking and
5，6 被按下了。那我们很了不起哦
rolling here. We're able to collect the digits from user.
我们能够成功地接收用户按下按钮上的数字
Now let's put them in the calculator display.
现在我们把这些数字展示出来
So we need to add a display to our calculator.
所以我们要给我们的计算器加一个显示屏
So we're gonna go back to our area here.
先调出工具区
Go down to the bottom half. Now be careful not to grab
把下半部分的对象库拽出来。注意我们要使用的
text field here because that's editable text and
不是这里的这个 Text Field。那是用来输入文字的
in a calculator you can't click on the display and
正常的计算器是不应该
edit it. You type the numbers to put your numbers in. So
让你点击显示屏修改结果的。你应该按数字按钮
we're gonna use this one up here, which is label.
正确的选择是使用上面这个，Label
By the way, if you click on one of these and
顺便提一句，如果你点击这些对象中的其中一个
leave your mouse there for a second,
然后把鼠标就停留在那里
it'll give you a detailed explanation of each of these
Xcode 会详细地解释
objects in the list. So I'm just gonna pick out a label
任何一个在列表中的对象。我按住这个 Label
and drag it up here to top,
然后拖过来放在最上面
maybe make a little more space for it. Move out a little bit.
稍微多给它留点空间，把这些挪下来些
So we've got this label. Once again just like I did for
我们已经添加了这个标签，还是像之前一样
the buttons I'm going to change the size.
像更改按钮一样更改标签的大小
Maybe I want to start with zero in there. Bigger font.
把标签显示的文字改成 0，调大字号
Let's go over here maybe even really big font, like 40 or
还是点这个按钮，设置一个很大的字号，比如 40
something like that. In a calculator the text is right
在计算器中，显示器中的文字是右对齐的对吧
aligned. Right? Text comes out from the right, so
数字是从右边开始增加的
we want to use this alignment right here.
所以还应该调整这个对齐方式
Right aligned. Okay? Maybe with some colors.
改为右对齐。还可以改下颜色
Let's put, let's make the background be blue.
把背景色改成蓝色
But I don't really like black on blue, so
但是黑色的字就不够显眼了
we'll go up here and change the color to be white. Okay?
到上面来把字的颜色改成白色
So that's a pretty decent looking display
现在看起来就像样多了
right there, for now anyway. Now, if we have these
再挪上去点，先这样吧。如果我们
buttons being pressed, we need to talk to this display, and
按下按钮，就应该告诉这个显示屏
tell it what the digits are.
按下了哪个按钮
So how are we gonna do that? Well again,
怎么做呢？
we need to make a connection between that display and
我们需要把显示屏连接到代码里
our code. But this is not the same kind of connection.
但用的和之前是不同的一种连接
Because we don't touch on that label, and
因为我们不会按下显示屏
it calls a method, We need to have an instance variable, or
然后让它调用一个方法。我们需要一个实例变量
property, that points to that thing, so we can talk to it
也就是指向这个显示屏的属性，然后我们就能
whenever we want, cuz we gotta put these digits on it.
随时在代码中向这个显示屏添加数字了
Okay? So we're still going to use the same mechanism to
连接的方法还是和之前一样
make a connection, which is control. And we're going to
按下 Control 键
drag in here. Okay? And this time we're going to use
然后拖到代码这边来，不过 Connection 选择
outlet. Outlet means a property that points to this.
Outlet，创建一个指向它的属性
And I'm going to call this display. It's our display.
名字就叫做 display，这是我们的显示屏
It got the type right here. This weak and strong, don't
这里的类型已经自动选好了，下面的 Weak 和 Strong
worry about that. I'm going to talk about that next week.
暂时不需要管，下周才会讲到
Okay. So don't worry. So, here is
所以不用担心
our first instance variable in our class. Woo hoo! Okay?
哇哦！第一个类的实例变量
This right here, is again just some stuff that Xcode
当然，@IBOutlet 是 Xcode 的标记
throws in there, so you get this, right? This,
让它显示这个小圆点
I told you ignore, okay? So
你们不需要在意这个
this is the declaration of our property and
这部分是属性的定义
of course it's a var and that could be let. If you want
当然，是个变量，其实用 let 也行
an instance variable that is set at the beginning and
如果你的实例变量始终是初始值
never changes, you can use let. It's pretty rare, but
一直没变过就可以用 let，不过很少见
you can do it, okay usually they're var. Display,
你可以这么做，不过一般都是 var
that's the name. ": UILabel!" is the type,
变量叫 display，: UILabel! 说的是它的类型
okay? So as you might guess, this has something to do with
好吧？你应该会想到可选类型
optionals, okay? This is kinda confusing to
一开始就要马上理解是不可能的
start off the bat, but that exclamation point,
虽然这个感叹号
which normally means unwrap an optional. Obviously we can't
一般是用来强制解包的，但显然这里
unwrap here, we're declaring this thing here.
我们不是在解包，我们是在定义变量
This is pretty much exactly the same as a question mark.
这个的意思和问号是差不多的
In fact, I'm gonna change it to a question mark for
实际上，现在我要把它改成问号
now, and later I'll change it back to an exclamation point,
之后再改回来
and you'll see the difference. But, the type of this display
然后你就能看出区别了。但无论如何
is optional UI label. Now, why is this an optional UI label?
display 都是可选的 UILabel。为什么呢？
Why isn't this just a UILabel?
为什么就不能只是 UILabel 呢？
Why does it have to be optional? Because when this UI
为什么要是可选呢？因为当用户界面
first comes up, iOS needs a few nanoseconds to hook
刚显示的时候，系统需要一点时间
that up for you. So when this UI first comes up,
关连控件和代码。所以刚加载的时候
it's not set to an optional not set case and then UI hooks
它是缺省值的。关连完之后
it up for you, and now it's set forever after that. And
之后就是有值的了
that's important that it's set forever, and we'll see it has
之后一直都是有值的。
to do with that exclamation point I just got rid of. But
这就是我刚才去掉的那个感叹号的作用
for now understand that display is just an optional
现在只要理解这是可选类型就行了
we'll have to unwrap it every time we use it, okay so
每次使用的时候都要解包
as simple as that. All right, so now instead of printing
仅此而已。现在我们
the digits on the screen let's go ahead and
不打印数字到控制台了
put these digits into the display,
我们把数字加到显示屏上
and really every time a digit is pressed we wanna append it
每次按下某个数字
onto the end of the display like if there's 56 in there we
就把它加到显示屏最后。比如现在是 56
wanna append 2- it's 562 and 8 it's 5268, right? So we're
我们要加个 2，就是 562；再加个 8，就是 5268
just gonna keep appending. So we need to get the text so
我们就一直往后面加。所以我们就要获取当前
it's currently in the display and add the digit to it.
display 显示的文字，然后把数字加到后面
So I'm gonna add another little local variable.
所以我们还需要一个局部变量
It's a constant also called textCurrentlyInDisplay and
一个叫做 textCurrentlyInDisplay 的常量
I'm gonna get that by sending a message to the display,
得到它的值，是通过发送消息到 display
which I have to unwrap,
当然要先解包
and now I can send your message. And
然后再发送消息
here's all the messages that label responds too,
然后这些就是标签所有会响应的消息了
again, hundreds, okay? So I'm gonna do the same trick, I'm
也是有一大堆，好吧。还是用老方法
gonna type text because I want the text out of there Look at
我输入 text，文字就是我想要的
the very first one, the text displayed by the label.
看看这第一个，标签显示的文字
It's an optional string. Excellent, I'll take it, okay.
可选类型的字符串。很好，就决定是你了
So, now I've got the text but it's optional. So,
我得到了显示的文字，但是是可选的
I need to unwrap it, okay? So now textCurrentlyInDisplay.
我需要解包 textCurrentlyInDisplay
If I option click on it you'll see it's a string. So,
如果我按 Option 键再点击它，类型就只是字符串了
now I can just say, set the display, unwrap,
我现在就只需要把 display 解包
text equal to the text that's currently in the display
赋值 text 为 display 现在的文字
plus the digit. Now, notice when I set an optional, text
加上数字。注意当我赋值给一个可选类型时
is an optional, right? When I set it equal to something- by
text 是可选的，是吧？我赋值给它的时候
the way this optional is get and set unlike currentTitle,
顺便说一句，text 是可读写的
which was get only- so I can set the your label's text here
不像只读的 currentTitle。所以我们能够更改标签的文字
and get it. When I set this optional right here,
也能得到它。当我赋值给可选类型的时候
I don't have to unwrap it first, okay?
我并不需要先解包
So you don't have to unwrap an optional to set it,
所以赋值给可选类型的时候不需要解包
you just set it. And optionals know okay,
你直接赋值就可以了。因为可选类型已经知道了
this must be the associated value of an optional string,
这个值也一定是可选字符串类型的
so I will set it, okay? So that's it,
所以我可以直接赋值给它，这样就可以了
let's see if that works. Okay,
让我们看看有没有用
so we got our UI, looks good, got a display in there, mm-hm.
我们的界面显示出来了，显示屏也在上面
Let's try 8, well 6, well, it's kinda working.
让我们按 8，6。好吧，虽然没什么大问题
It's definitely doing the appending thing,
因为我们按的数字确实添加在了后面
but that 0 at the beginning,
不过一开始的那个 0
that's wrong. That zero is not part of what I was typing.
那是不对的，那并不是我输入的一部分
That zero just happened to be there at startup.
那个 0 是我一开始默认显示的
So, it shouldn't be put in in the front there and
所以它并不应该一直显示在前面
the problem here is really simple.
这个问题很容易解决
It's just that we haven't taught our calculator to know
只不过是我们还没有教会计算器
when the user is entering,
哪个部分才是用户输入的
in the middle of entering a number,
什么时候用户正在输入
versus when it just started up.
什么时候它刚开始运行
Or maybe, the result of an operation just appeared
或者显示屏刚显示运算的结果
there. Obviously when we type we wouldn't want that to
当然我们输入的时候
happen, thanks to it. So, we need to teach our
并不希望 0 出现在前面。所以我们
calculator brain here to know the difference between whether
要让计算器有不同的状态
the user is in the middle of typing or not.
知道用户是否在输入的过程中
And we're gonna do that, by creating another property
实现的方法是定于另一个属性
called userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping.
叫做 userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping
Which is gonna be a Bool. Now, I typed a long name here. Kind
一个 Bool 类型的属性。这名字挺长的
of for effect. We probably could have called this typing.
我这是为了舞台效果。多半我们可以就叫它 typing 就行了
You know, there's trade off between clarity and brevity.
清晰和简洁不可兼得
Okay, brevity is valued, but clarity is even more
当然简洁很重要，不过表达明确更重要
important. So, maybe isTyping would have been enough.
也许 isTyping 就够了的
But I would err slightly on the side of clarity. So I'm
但我还是更偏向于表达清晰
using this long one. The other thing, the reason I typed this
所以我会用这个很长的名字。另一个原因是
long is to show you that I'm never gonna have to type this
告诉你我从来不需要再完整地敲这么长的名字
again, because Xcode is always gonna escape complete this for
因为 Xcode 会帮我自动补全
me, as you'll see when I start using it. Now when I added
当我用到的时候就你们就知道了
this beautiful var, this Bool. Okay, a Bool, by the way,
当我添加这个美丽的布尔型变量之后
is just something that can be true or false,
也就是只能为 true 和 false 的变量之后
of course. I got an error. Look at that error up there.
出现了错误。看看这里的这个错误
This little thing here- it's on a line that had nothing to
这里的这个小标记，出现在了这一行
do with what I just did. What? That's not fair.
和我刚才干的那行毫无关系的地方。这就奇怪了
What is this? It says Class 'View Controller'
它说什么？它说 Class 'ViewController' has no initializers
has no initializers. Okay well, what the heck is that?
ViewController 类没有构造器。这是什么意思？
That has nothing to do with the var either?
这和我们刚定义的变量也没关系啊
Well, here's the deal here. In Swift,
好吧，事情是这样的
all properties have to be initialized. Every single one.
Swift 要求所有的属性都要初始化。每个都要
No exceptions. Now there's two ways
一个都不能少。可以使用两种方法
to initialize your properties in a class or struct.
来初始化类和结构体里的属性
One is with an initializer.
一是使用构造器
An initializer is a special method, it's called init,
构造器是一个特殊的方法，叫做 init
I-N-I-T. You can have any number of arguments that your
I-N-I-T。可以接受任意数量的参数
class requires but, in its implementation it has to
只要是这个类需要的；但一定要保证
initialize all uninitialized properties. Okay? Now,
初始化所有没有初始化的属性
we're not gonna talk about initializers today.
我们今天不会讲构造器
I'll talk about it a little bit next Wednesday,
我们下周三会讲一点
actually. So, we're not gonna use an initializer. Because
所以我们今天不会用构造器
there's a second way to initialize, which is to just
因为我们还有第二种方法来初始化
give it a value. Okay, is false, right? The user's
直接赋值就可以了。我们这里设置为 false
obviously not in the middle of typing at the beginning, so
因为一开始的时候用户肯定没有在输入
is false. And that got rid of the error.
所以是 false。错误就解决了
Okay? In fact, we don't need this either. Do you see why?
其实，我们也不需要声名类型，知道为什么吗？
Because false, can only be a Bool, So
因为 false 是 Bool 类型的
Swift can infer that this must be a Bool. And again,
Swift 能够自动推导类型，知道这个一定是布尔型的
we do not want these things in here, if we can help it. Now,
所以如果可能的话，我们习惯不声明类型
what about this guy? That's not initialized. How come he's
那这个 display 呢？它也没有初始化啊
not complaining, okay? How come he's not getting that?
为什么没有报错呢？这不公平
Must be initializers business going on. Well, because he's
使用了构造器么？其实原因是因为它是
an optional. And optionals are special when it comes
可选类型的。可选类型很特别
to initialization. They all get this automatic treatment.
初始化的时候会被自动
Equals nil. nil means not set optional. Okay.
初始化为 nil。nil 表示缺省值
That's the only thing nil means in Swift. It means
nil 在 Swift 里的意思就是缺省值
an optional that's not set. So optional will automatically
表示可选类型没有被赋值。所以在定义
get this treatment at all times when you declare them.
可选类型时都会自动被初始化为 nil
And it makes sense right, if you have an optional
这是很有道理的。你有一个可选类型
it's gonna start out not set until you set it.
一开始是没有值的，直到你赋值给它
Now you could set this equal to some UILabel of some sort,
当然你也可以初始化为某个 UILabel 实例
and have it be set from the start, that's possible too.
一开始就有值是可能的
But if you don't say anything it gets not set. Alright, so
但如果没有的话，那就是缺省值
we've got that. Now we can use this userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping
好，大家都明白了。我们现在就可以用 userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping 了
thing. We'll say if the user is
如果用户正在输入的中途
in the middle of typing then we can do,
if userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping
this business that we just did here, okay?
然后我们再进行下面的这些操作
What if it's not in the middle of typing? Then we're just
那如果并没有开始输入呢？那我们
gonna set the display's text equal to the digit, cuz we're
赋值显示屏的文字为当前按下的数字
starting a new number then. In this case of course,
我们从头开始输入一个数字。这种情况下
the user is now in the middle of typing Okay,
用户就在输入的过程中了，为 true
everybody got that? So that's just how we're going to make
大家都还跟的上吧？这就是我们确保
sure we do the right thing. So let's go ahead and run,
计算器正常显示的方法。让我们运行
see if that whole 0, leading 0 problem is fixed.
看看开头显示 0 的问题是否解决了
Should be, because when we start off,
应该是的，因为一开始的时候
we're not in the middle of typing. So
用户并不是在输入的过程中
when we start typing a new number, boom,
当我们输入第一个数字
we get a new number. But if we're in the middle of typing,
就替换为了我们这个数字。但如果我们在输入的过程中
we keep getting the appending deal. All right,
我们会向后面添加数字
we are just rocking and rolling here.
我们这一步算是完成了
Next, let's put some operation buttons in this baby.
下一步，我要放一些运算符在这里
We can type in numbers, now let's start operating.
我们已经能输入数字了，下一步就是运算
I'm gonna do that by doing a very bad thing,
接下来我要干一件非常不好的事
which is I'm going to copy and paste the 7 button.
那就是复制粘贴这个数字 7 按钮
You're gonna see why that's bad in a moment. And
马上你们马上就知道这为什么是不好的做法
I'm gonna do a very simple operation, pi, okay?
我就加一个非常简单的运算符派吧，π，Option+P
So pi is just an operation that's gonna put pi in my
派就是在显示屏中显示派的数值
display, that's all it's gonna do. So I'm gonna control drag
这就是它的功能。我还是按住 Control 然后拖到代码里
to wire it up to a method. It's an action, not an outlet.
让它关连一个方法。选的是 Action，不是 Outlet
It's an action, just like touchDigit was.
就像是 touchDigit 一样的方法
I'm gonna call it performOperation,
方法叫做 perfomOperation
cuz that's what it does, it performs an operation.
这就是它的功能，进行某个运算
I'm gonna make sure I switch this to button like you
我会像作业里要求你们的那样
guys all are in your homework assignments. And
把这个改成 UIButton
then I'm going to connect. So now I have this new method
然后点 Connect。新的函数就定义好了
right here, and it is hooked up to pi, so that's good.
和这个派按钮连起来的
And what do I want to do in here?
要实现什么功能呢？
Well, I could do the same thing of asking the button
我可以像之前一样
which operation it is. How about let mathematicalSymbol,
问这个按钮你是什么运算。要不然用 let mathematicalSymbol
because that's what these things are in these operation
因为这些按钮的标题就是数学运算符
buttons, equal the sender.currentTitle!, okay?
把 sender.currentTitle! 赋值给这个常量
Great, now I've got the pi, but I wanted to show you,
好，我现在得到派了，不过我像给你们看看
I promised I'd show you how to do this unwrapping without
就像我之前说的那样，教你们如何解包
crashing, so let's do it here. Let's decide that if we do
又不用导致崩溃。我就用这个来演示。让我们来判断
have a blank button, a button whose title is not set, let's
这是否是个空白的按钮，这个按钮是否有标题
say we won't crash. Instead, we'll just do nothing.
如果是的话我们什么都不做就行了，不崩溃
We won't do any operations.
我们什么运算都不进行
Like you didn't even click a button, okay?
就像用户就没按这个按钮一样
So, again, optionals are so important. You can see,
再次强调，可选类型是很重要的
look how minuscule the syntax is for these things, right?
看看这些不起眼的语法
Question mark. Exclamation point. You barely have to type
问号，感叹号。使用可选类型并不需要
to use an optional. Well, it's the same thing if you want to
额外太多的代码。我们想要在解包
test the optional before unwrapping.
可选类型前，判断其是否为空
Instead of putting the exclamation point at the end,
我们不用感叹号
you put two characters at the beginning. if. So
我们只要在前面加两个字母，if
read this. If I can let mathematical symbol equal
连起来读，如果我能让数学运算符等于
the sender's currentTitle, then. So,
调用函数按钮当前的标题，那么怎样
if I can unwrap this optional, get its associated value,
也就是如果我能够解包这个可选类型，获得它的关联值
then I'll do something, and
那么我就干这些
then you can just put whatever code you want in here,
然后你就可以在这里面
and inside here,
使用这个解包的可选类型了
mathematicalSymbol will be a string, the associated value.
mathematicalSymbol 就是关联值，那个普通的字符串
The unwrapped optional, right? Outside of these curly braces,
已经解包的可选类型。大括号以外
mathematicalSymbol is not even defined, so it doesn't matter.
mathematicalSymbol 是未定义的，所以不用担心
It's not even defined. So
它是未定义的
inside this mathematicalSymbol, I could
在这个大括号里面
say if mathematicalSymbol equals, pi, then do something.
我可以判断，如果数学符号是派，我就这样
Else if the mathematical symbol equals something else,
否则如果是这个，否则如果是这样一直判断下去
okay? But, if then else, if then else, if then else, that
if...else if...else if...
would be really bad code. So I'm going to use a different
这样的代码看起来糟糕极了。所以我要换一种
one here. A different little expression.
另外一种表达式
I'm going to use switch. So a lot of languages have switch.
我要使用的是 switch 语句，许多语言都有 switch
So I'm going to switch on the mathematical symbol.
我会尝试匹配这个数学符号
Not all languages can switch on a string. Some can, but
并不是所有的语言都能匹配字符串的，有些能
you can in Swift. And I can just say, in the case that
比如 Swift 语言就可以。我能直接用 case "π"
it is pi, then I'm going to do something. Now,
如果是派的话，我就这样做
unfortunately I'm getting an error here.
然而 Xcode 报错了
So, what am I gonna do? Let's just put in what I'm gonna do.
那我想干什么？我们还是先把这部分加进去吧
I just want the display. Woops, the displays, text to
我们就让显示屏的文字
equal pi. Okay. This is pretty bad to type it in as a string,
赋值为派，3.1415926。这样直接输入挺不规范的
we'll get back to that in a second.
我们等会儿来解决这个问题
But that's basically what I wanted to do, right?
但这就是我要做的
Is set the display to be pi. Now I'm getting an error.
让显示屏显示派。但还是报错
What is the error? It says switch has to be exhaustive.
什么原因？它说 Switch must be exhaustive
And that's true. When you have a switch, you have to have
是这样的，用 switch 语句的时候，一定要
every possible case. So unless we want to spend the next few
能包含所有的情况。我们也许可以花上
lectures I guess going like this, case a-a-a, and
接着的几节课的时间，输入比如 case "aaa"
typing any possible string, okay, this is no good. So
输入所有可能出现的字符串。这当然是不可能的
luckily though, there is a default case. So
幸运的是，我们可以用 default
default just means all other cases.
也就是其它的所有情况
And here I'm just gonna break out of the switch.
我就 break，跳出这个 switch 语句
I'm gonna use this command break. Now notice that my
就用 break 关键字。注意到我这里
indentation's gotten a little messed up here. This should
代码的对齐有点乱了，这里
really be the same indentation as this. A really cool feature
和这里应该是对齐的。Xcode 有个很棒的功能
is select any text you want, even the whole file, and
那就是你能选中任意的代码，甚至整个文件
do Ctrl I for indent, and it will re-indent everything for
然后按 Control+I 自动对齐。Xcode 就会帮你对齐
you. And I recommend you do that on all your source files
我建议你们对你所有作业里的每个代码文件
when you turn in your homework. Just select all,
都 Command+A 全选，然后自动对齐
indent. So we got this pi here. Let's see if this works.
我们已经添加了派的相关逻辑，来看看能不能用
Got the numbers are still working.
按钮还是没问题
And pi. Okay. That's weird.
再试试派。这就怪了
I got that pi that I typed in right here. Okay, but
显示了我这里输入的派的值
what, how come I got this pi symbol added on there?
但为什么后面还有一个派的符号呢
That seems weird. Let's try a new number. So, no, okay.
这真奇怪。我们再试个数字。这下糟了
When I type more numbers, it adds it on to the end. So
我按了数字之后，还是加在显示屏的后面
even if that pi symbol wasn't in there,
即使那个派的符号不在那里
I'd be able to change the value of pi,
我也能更改派的值
evidently by adding more digits to it. That's no good.
随便给它加个几位数，这可不行
And look at this. When I type more it puts an ellipsis,
再看看这个，我再多加几位小数
and it stops taking numbers. Okay, this is a mess.
它就不显示了，这可真是一团糟
We got three big problems here. That pi.
我们有三个大问题。一，那个派
The fact that I can add on things to the end of it,
二，能向派后面加小数位
and the fact that I get these ellipses.
三，会出现省略号
So how are we going to fix those?
怎么解决呢？
Let's go fix all three of those real quick. Okay. So,
我们抓紧时间一起解决吧
first the pi coming on the end. Well look,
先是这个结尾出现派的问题
where do I ever set the display sets? I set it here.
我在哪里更改过显示屏的内容？这里
Well, so clearly the pi's not coming from this.
但派的符号肯定不是从这里来的
I set it here. This only sets it to one digit so
这里也改过，但是这里只会是显示一个数字
that can't be it, cuz I've got multiple.
肯定不是这里，因为我这里不只是一位数
This is the only other place I set it. Maybe
那只剩下这里了
this is the problem. Do you see the pi button right there?
也许就是它了。看到派按钮了吗？
It's hooked up to this method. And to this method. So
它也和这个函数关连上了，也关连了这个函数
it's doing both. It's doing this and putting this on here,
所以两个函数的内容都在执行。先是执行这个部分，显示了派的数值
and then it's calling this, and doing this. And
然后又调用了这个方法，把派加到了后面
the digit is the pi, okay? So, that's bad. Now, how are we
这里的数字，其实是派符号。这就是问题
going to fix that? Question? >> How did you set
怎么解决？同学，什么问题？>> 你是怎么设置
the order range? >> Yeah,
顺序的？
the question is how did it decide the order?
>> 我重复下，问题是调用方法的顺序是怎么决定的
And the answer is the order is undefined.
答案是不确定的
In my experience, it's usually alphabetical, but
据我的经验，通常是按字母顺序
it's undefined. So you would never wanna depend on that.
但并没有一个统一的标准。所以你最好不要依靠调用的顺序
But yeah, perform comes before touchDigit.
这里 performOperation 是在 touchDigit 之前
I don't know. But you're almost never gonna have two
我也不知道。一般来说不会像这样
things hooked up like this. This is obviously an error.
和两个方法都关连起来。我们这里肯定是有问题的
This is causing a problem. So let's fix it. How do we do
导致程序出了问题，所以我们需要解决这个问题。
that? There's another way to know what's connected other
怎么办？其实还有另一种查看关连的方法
than using the little circles, which is just to right click
除了用这个小圆点之外，还能直接右键点击
on something in the UI. So I right clicked on pi, and I got
界面里的控件。比如我右键点击派
this big window that shows me all the connections to pi.
就出现这个很大的窗口，列出了所有和它的关连
This would be all the instance variables, all the methods,
也就是关连着的实例变量和方法
etc. And we can see that for the event Touch Up Inside,
这里也列出了所有 Touch Up Inside
which means a touch of the finger went up inside
也就是手指抬起的时候
the bounds of the button. It's sending both these messages,
如果在按钮内部，就发出消息
touchDigit and perfomOperation, and
给 touchDigit 和 performOperation
we clearly did not want touchDigit for pi.
我们显然不希望派按钮调用 touchDigit
Why did I get it? Because I copied and pasted that 7.
但我为什么会有这个关连呢？是因为我是复制粘贴的数字 7
Remember I said that was a bad idea? Yeah, that's why. So
还记得我说那是个坏主意吗？这就是原因
let's disconnect it by just clicking this little x, okay,
我们点这个小叉，取消关连
boom. Now this only is sent by this, and not by this.
现在就只会发消息给 performOperation，不会给 touchDigit 了
So that fixed that. What about the fact that
第一个问题就解决了。那我能够
I could type extra numbers on the end of pie? Well, that's
给派再加个几位的问题呢？
a pretty simple neither. When am I allowed to type other
这也很容易解决。我什么时候可以向显示屏
numbers in? When the user's in the middle of typing a number.
加数字？当用户正在输入的时候
Well as soon as I hit pi,
用户按下派之后
is the user in the middle of typing a number? No, they
还在输入的过程中吗？没有
just typed pi. So they're not in the middle of typing pi.
他们已经输入完派了，他们并不是在输入派的过程中
And in fact, they're typing a number.
他们没有还在输入一个数字
And in fact any time we perform any operation,
其实我们在进行任何运算的时候
the user is in the middle of typing a number is false.
就可以让 userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping = false
They are clearly not in the middle of typing anymore.
因为用户显然已经还在输入的过程中了
Whatever's gonna be display is gonna be the result of that
显示的内容只会是运算的结果
operation. Okay, so that fixes that. How bout the little
好，解决了第二个问题。那省略号呢
ellipses, and the numbers getting cut off. Well here's
那些被截断的数字呢
a kind of a cute fix to that. In label, there is a cool
我们解决的方法挺机智的。标签里有个很酷的功能
feature called autoshrink, you see it right there?
叫做 Autoshrink，自动缩小，看到了吗
So I just selected label, brought up this inspector.
选中一个标签，调出检查器
There's autoshrink, and you can have it shrink down, for
找到这里的 Autoshrink。你可以选择缩小到
example to a minimum font size, let's say 9 font.
比如说某个字号，像是 9 号
And now, when we get too many numbers,
我们现在数字多起来之后
it'll shrink down instead of doing ellipses, right there.
它就会自动缩小，而不是显示省略号了
Now, this probably isn't the best solution to this.
但这并不一定是最好的解决方案
A better solution would be, have our calculator only show
更好的方法是，让计算器只显示
a certain number of digits after the decimal point.
一定长度的数字，或是只到小数点后几位
Probably would be really better. And
这样也许会更好
that's extra credit for you in your homework, okay?
这会作为你们作业里的加分项
So good luck with that. Right, so we got this.
祝你们好运吧。我们稍作修改
We fixed all these problems, let's take a look.
解决了所有的问题，来实际看看吧
All right, so got our numbers here. Pi, alright no pi and
数字键还是正常的。派，太好了，没有结尾的符号了
it didn't add them on to the end and
再按数字键也不是加在派后面了
what if we had a lot of numbers in here.
再看看如果有很多数字呢
Yeah, look at that, it's autoshrinking.
很好，看看啊，字号在自动缩小
Okay, we're not losing any numbers.
没有出现数字消失的情况
Yeah, probably not the best solution but
虽然这不是最好的解决方案
I get to show you autoshrink. Okay, what's next?
我就是想展示一下自动缩小。下一步
We're gonna attack this little problem right here. Okay?
解决这个问题
This is really ugly, really what I want this to be is this
这实在是太丑陋了，我想让它改成这样
really cool feature in Swift, Double.pi, which is the double
Swift 里很优秀的特性，Double.pi
precision floating point value of pi. Of course, I can't say
派在双精度下的浮点值。当然我不能直接就这样写
this because- Cannot assign value of type 'Double' to
Cannot assign value of type 'Double' to type 'String?'
an optional string because the only way you can assign
不能把双精度类型的值赋给可选字符串
anything to an optional string besides nil would be something
因为可选字符串的值不是 nil 的话
that's a string. So we can set that associated value. Now,
就只能是字符串。所以我们要设置的就是那个关联值
does anyone know, from what I've shown you today,
有谁知道，我今天讲过的哪个内容
how we could convert this to a string? No brave soul?
能够把这个转换成字符串？没有人自告奋勇？
Back, exactly. Backslash, open parentheses,
没错，就是反斜线，左括号
close parenthesis, that little trick, right?
右括号，就是这个窍门
You can just put Double.pi in here.
然后把 Double.pi 放进来
Doubles can be converted to strings, bingo.
双精度小数可以转换成一个字符串
Now, this is kinda ugly, okay? This really doesn't look good
但这看起来也不是很好
because this is more meant to embed things in other strings.
因为这个适用于把其它东西插入到字符串里
It's not really the way to make something a string.
而不是把它转换成字符串的方法
The way to really make a new string is to create
新建一个字符串的方法
a new string. And so, here you're seeing what the syntax
是构造一个字符串。你这里看到的
is to create a new object, a new struct or a new class,
就是构造一个新对象的方法，一个新的结构体或类的方法
okay? The name of the class, and then parentheses.
类的名字，然后是一对括号
Now, inside these parentheses, can be anything the class
在括号里面是任何
can take to create one of itself, right? Anything that
可以用来构造对象的参数
class can take. And remember I mentioned those initializers?
任何支持的参数。还记得我提到的构造器吗
These are the arguments to the initializer. And initializers,
这些就是构造器的参数
you've got multiple initializers.
你可以有许多不同的构造器
String has a whole bunch of initializers.
字符串类有不少的构造器
One of the initializers that a string has,
其中一个
takes a double. So this would be the right way to
能接受一个双精度小数。所以这才是
convert from a double to a string and
把双精度小数转换为字符串的方法
it looks a lot better in the code as well, right.
代码也看起来好多了
It's more obvious what we're doing, okay?
我们的意图也更明显了
All right let's add another operation here,
我们再来添加另一个运算
I'm gonna make this one be square root. So I'm gonna need
平方根。我需要这个符号
the square root symbol, from the edit menu, emoji and
从菜单里的 Edit > Emoji & Symbols
symbols, you can actually search. We could pick a smiley
然后搜索。虽然我们可以就用这个笑脸符号
face but let's go square root. Square root, here it is, so
但我们还是把平方根找出来。square root，出来了
we're gonna use this square root symbol in code there. And
我们就使用这个平方根符号
let's go ahead and copy it so we can use it in the code.
然后 Command+C 复制到剪贴板，等会在代码里用
All right, so we have this,
这就是我们的平方根按钮
it's nicely hooked up just to this and not to this.
与且仅与 performOperation 关连
So that's good. We just need to say case of square root.
我们 switch 再加一个情况，如果是平方根，case "√"
What do we wanna do? We wanna set the display's text
我们就把显示的文字
equal to the square root of something. Okay, well what do
赋值为某个数的平方根
we want this to be the square root of? Well we want it to be
我们希望这是什么的平方根？
the square root of whatever's in this display already. So,
应该是目前显示屏内容的平方根
display!.text, okay, will that work? No, because this
能直接把 display!.text 作为参数吗
is a string and we can't take the square root of a string.
不行，因为那是个字符串，怎么计算一个字符串的平方根啊
And not only that, the square root returns a double, okay?
还有一个问题，sqrt 的返回值是双精度型的
And we can't put a double into a string, so we at least have
我们不能把它赋值给一个字符串
to do this again, put a string around it. Okay? But
所以我们至少需要用 String 的构造器
this is still a string. So I'm gonna get this out of here and
但这个部分还是字符串。先把这个部分单独出来
make a little local variable so
存到一个局部变量 operand
we can work on this, okay? So, we need this operand,
只关注这个部分。我们需要这个运算数
which is currently a string, to be a double. So
operand 由现在的字符串变为小数
can we do this, double? You think we can do that?
我们能把它转换为双精度小数吗？
In the same way that we went this way? Can we go this way?
能像我们转字符串那样吗？能反过来吗？
The answer is yes. Or yes? One of those.
答案是可以，更准确地说，大部分时候可以
The answer is yes because, what if that string is hello?
因为，如果那个字符串是 hello
What do you convert hello to? It can't be converted.
你要怎么把 hello 转成小数？这是做不到的
So this initializer for double that takes a string,
所以这个双精度的构造器，参数是字符串
it returns an optional double. Do you see why? Cuz if you
返回值是一个可选的双精度。可以理解吧
give it a string that it can't convert to a double,
给它个字符串，如果没法转换
it returns not set. Couldn't do it, basically.
返回就会缺省值。也就是表示无法转换
So if we look at operand right here, it's an optional double,
所以我们可以看到这个 operand，是 Double? 类型的
okay? Whereas when we did this string up here,
和上面字符串的构造器是不一样的
string didn't need to return optional string,
构造的并不会是可选字符串
because it can always convert a double to a string, always.
因为一定能用字符串表示小数
But you can't always convert a string to a double,
但不总是能把字符串转换成小数的
it has to look like a double. Okay?
至少要长得像才行
So, we're gonna do that and I'm gonna go ahead and
我们就用这个构造器
force unwrap it here with the exclamation point, assuming
直接用感叹号强制解包
that I never have anything in my display that can't be
假设显示的内容
converted to a double. Maybe that's a bad assumption but
总是能转换的。虽然这个假设很大胆
I'm gonna assume that for now. I'm also gonna Ctrl+I again,
但现在先这样吧。还是顺便用 Control+I
to get my indenting right. Okay, does this make sense?
把代码对齐。都还能理解吧？
So now all is well. Operand is a double.
这样就完成了，operand 是 Double 型的
So I can take the square root of a double.
我就能直接求它的平方根了
I'm gonna convert it to a string and go to here.
再转成字符串显示出来
All right, wow, that's a lot of mess. Okay,
有够混乱的
that's really messy code, I'm gonna have to fix that, but
我有必要整理一下这堆混乱的代码
conceptually you understand hopefully what's going on
但希望你们能理解这里发生了什么
there. So let's do this, let's try 81 square root. Square
让我们来试试，81，平方根
root again. Square root again. How about pi square root?
再平方根，再平方根。派的平方根
78 square root? All right, this is working perfectly.
78 的平方根。一切正常
But, our code is really a mess here. Can you imagine,
只不过代码有些乱。你想象一下
if we have to do another case and another case.
如果我们还有另外好几种情况
And we're always doing this double this, string that,
我们就需要不断地转换成 Double 再转回 String
back and forth, exclamation points everywhere. Okay,
每个地方都强制解包
there's too many dang exclamation points in here for
有太多不安全的感叹号
the first thing. And the second of all,
这是第一个问题。第二个问题是
I'm tired of all the strings and doubles. So
转换过来转换过去太麻烦了
I'm gonna fix all that. Let's start with the exclamation
两个问题都要解决。从感叹号开始
point thing. Look at every time I use the display.
仔细观察，我每次用 display 的时候
I use it all over my code.
可以看出我到处都在用
And every time I have to put an exclamation point,
每次用都有感叹号
every single time. Even though I know that display,
每次都强制解包，即使我知道
once it's set up by iOS in the beginning, it never is not in
只要 iOS 系统完成初始化之后
the not set state, it's always set. So
display 总是存在的，不会出现缺省值的情况
let's go back up here to this question mark.
我们回到这个问号
This is what exclamation point in a declaration
这就是在定义的时候使用感叹号的原因
of an optional means. It means yes, this is an optional,
对于定义可选类型而言，这个感叹号
just like a question mark. But, everywhere you use this,
和问号是差不多的。只不过每次使用的时候
I'm going to automatically unwrap it. Now,
会自动强制解包
it's still unwrapping it, so even if I go down here and
因为会自动解包，所以我们把下面代码里
I take away this exclamation point,
所有 display 后面的感叹号都去掉
it works because of this automatic unwrapping.
还是能够正常运行的，因为都自动解包了
But if this were not set, it would still crash. Okay?
但即使如此，如果 display 缺省值的话，还是会崩溃的
Because essentially, implicitly unwrapping.
因为这实际上会隐式解包这个 display
That's why this is called an implicitly unwrapped optional.
这就是所谓的 implicitly unwrapped optional
Got that phrase? Implicitly unwrapped optional. But
隐式解析可选类型
it does mean, that we can go around to all of our
这意味着我们可以把所有的
display question marks, and change them to display.
display! 替换成 display
And that makes our code look quite a bit nicer. Okay?
这样代码看起来就好些了
Now we're still having to unwrap text. Sorry about that.
但我们还是要强制解包 text 的，没有办法
Bottom line is we have to do that.
下面的这行需要保留感叹号
That's not an implicitly unwrapped optional, that text.
text 并不是一个隐式解包的可选类型
Okay, what about all this double and string thing?
那这些来回转换的呢？
The way I'm gonna fix that is imagine I had a var.
解决方法是如果我能有个变量
We'll call it displayValue.
叫 displayValue，显示的数值
And it was a double. Okay, show me this var.
是 Double 类型的变量
Imagine if this var, always tracked, what's in here, but
如果它能够和显示屏的数值保持同步
as a double? Cuz what's in there, we can only get it as
并以小数存储该多好。现在我们获取显示的值只能是字符串
a string, we can only set it as a string. But
也只能设置为一个字符串
wouldn't it be cool if I had a var that just was always what
我能不能有这样一个神奇的变量
was in there but as a double? Because I need it as a double
值总是显示屏里的小数？因为我每次使用的时候
all the dang time, and I need to set it as a double too,
我总是需要小数，每次设置的时候也是小数
okay? So how can I do that? Well, turns out Swift
那要怎么做呢？Swift 里
has a really cool feature called computed properties.
有个很厉害的特性叫做，computed property，计算型属性
And all I need to do is put code after the property, and
只需要把代码放到变量后面的那对大括号里
you can compute the value. Instead of storing
就能实时计算变量的值了，而不是依靠存储的值
it, right. The user is in the middle of typing a value that
userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping 这个变量的值
storage somewhere. This one we're gonna compute. And
是存储在某个地方的，displayValue 则是我们计算的
you can compute both a get case, right? And,
我们既能计算，get，获取的值
oops, sorry. And a set case. So you can have some code that
也能计算，set，赋于的值。所以你可以有代码
deals with getting the value and with setting the value.
负责计算获取的值，也可以有代码处理赋值的情况
So we're not gonna ever store displayValue anywhere.
我们的 displayValue 并不会被存储起来
We're gonna get it and set it.
我们会处理访问和赋值的计算
And where are we gonna get it and set it from?
计算的数据源又是哪里呢？
From the text on the label. Right? So what does the get
是标签显示的文字。那该怎么写 getter？
look like? Well, we're just gonna return a double of
我们就 return，返回用小数表示的
the display's text, you don't have to unwrap display, but
显示屏的文字。不用解包 display
I do have to unwrap text. And I'm gonna force unwrap that.
但是要解包 text。然后强制解包这个整体
Again, I'm assuming there's always a string that
我还是假设显示的内容
can be interpreted as a double in there.
一定能被解析为一个双精度小数
Maybe I wanna change that assumption down the road, but
也许之后我会改主意
for now I'll do that. How about the set case?
但现在我还是这么做假设。那被赋值的时候怎么办呢？
In this set case, I'm gonna display, set the display's
在被赋值的时候，我让 display 的 text
text equal to a string that is the value that
赋值为一个字符串
people are trying to set the display value to.
字符串是我们想要显示屏接下来显示的值
So somewhere in the code, we write displayValue equals
也就是比如写 displayValue = 5
five. And here we have to put a five,
我们就把 5
a string five into the text of the display up here.
转换成字符串显示到显示屏
So what do we put inside this little string here. Well, for
那这个字符串构造器的参数写什么？
this set case, okay, of a computed property,
计算属性的 set 里
there's a special variable called newValue, and newValue
有个特殊的变量叫做 newValue
is always of the same type as what you're setting, and it is
newValue 和这个变量是同一个类型的
the value on the right hand side of an equals if someone
它就是那个在赋值语句右边的
says that this var equals something, okay? Awesome.
你让变量等于的那个值
Now that we have this displayValue and
现在这个 displayValue
it's always tracking that, we can use it down here.
会和显示屏保持同步，也能够在下面使用了
Look at this code, displayValue equals pi.
改成这样，displayValue = Double.pi，显示的值为派
Done, get rid of all this mess. displayValue equals
看看啊，这些就都不用了。显示的值等于它自己的平方根
the square root of the displayValue. All of a sudden,
displayValue = sqrt(displayValue)。一瞬间
the code down here has become essential, right?
就能抓住重点了
This is about the minimum you could possibly type to say
这几乎是你能用的最短的代码
that you wanted pi into the display. Right? And so, when I
来让显示屏显示派
do this display value equals, this code gets executed.
当我用 displayValue = 的时候，运行的是 set 里这段代码
When I get the display value here, this code gets executed.
我在这里访问 displayValue 的时候，运行的是 get 里这段代码
These are called computed properties. You're
这就是计算型变量
going to see them all over the place.
它们无处不在
You've already seen one. It's right here, currentTitle
你已经在这里看到过一个了，就是这个 currentTitle
is a computed property. It's computed by the button class.
它就是个由按钮类计算的计算属性
It figures out what the current title is on there and
它计算出现在按钮上的标题
returns it. So there's this is implemented with some
然后返回给你。具体的实现
code that says return whatever.
就会是 return 什么什么一类的
How do I know that? Because it's read-only. The only way
我怎么知道的？因为这是只读的，而只有计算属性能实现
to make a read-only var is using a computed property.
完全只读的。（可以更改 setter 的访问级别来实现伪只读）
All right, let's make sure we didn't break anything with our
让我们来确认一下有没有导致新 bug
code clean up there. All right, 89 looking good,
毕竟整理了代码。试试 89
square root, 81, square root, square root, square root.
平方根。81 的平方根，的平方根，的平方根
Pi 78 square root. Okay,
派，78，平方根。好
it's working. Okay, so that's a lot of stuff to digest,
没问题。我知道要消化的内容很多
I know. Let it all sink in. On Wednesday at the start,
你们花时间理解记忆。星期三一开始
I'm gonna talk to you about MVC, this design paradigm, and
要讲 MVC，那个设计模式
then we're gonna add MVC to this and
再运用 MVC
we're also gonna make sure that UI works on all devices.
最后确保 UI 适用于各种设备
Okay, see you then. >> For
好，下课
more, please visit us at stanford.edu.
>> 更多课程详见 stanford.edu